<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Addict Sci Clin Pract</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Addict Sci Clin Pract</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Addiction Science &amp; Clinical Practice</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1940-0632</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1940-0640</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4347513</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1940-0640-10-S1-A34</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1940-0640-10-S1-A34</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Meeting Abstract</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Community involvement in a juvenile partner justice behavioral health</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1">
          <name>
            <surname>Leukefeld</surname>
            <given-names>Carl</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>cleukef@uky.edu</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2">
          <name>
            <surname>Knight</surname>
            <given-names>Danica</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3">
          <name>
            <surname>Belenko</surname>
            <given-names>Steven</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4">
          <name>
            <surname>Robertson</surname>
            <given-names>Angela</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A5">
          <name>
            <surname>Wiley</surname>
            <given-names>Tisha</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I5">5</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A6">
          <name>
            <surname>Wasserman</surname>
            <given-names>Gail</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I6">6</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A7">
          <name>
            <surname>DiClemente</surname>
            <given-names>Ralph</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I7">7</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A8">
          <name>
            <surname>Brody</surname>
            <given-names>Gene</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I8">8</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A9">
          <name>
            <surname>Knudsen</surname>
            <given-names>Hannah</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="I1"><label>1</label>College of Medicine, University of Kentucky, Lexington, KY, 40506, USA</aff>
      <aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Institute of Behavioral Research, Texas Christian University, Fort Worth, TX, 76129, USA</aff>
      <aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Department of Criminal Justice, Temple University, Philadelphia, PA, 19122, USA</aff>
      <aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Mississippi State University, Starkville, MS, 39762, USA</aff>
      <aff id="I5"><label>5</label>Services Research Branch, National Institute on Drug Abuse, Rockville, MD, 20852, USA</aff>
      <aff id="I6"><label>6</label>Columbia University, New York, NY, 10027, USA</aff>
      <aff id="I7"><label>7</label>Emory University, Atlanta, GA, 30322, USA</aff>
      <aff id="I8"><label>8</label>Institute for Behavioral Research, University of Georgia, Athens, GA, 30602, USA</aff>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>20</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>10</volume>
      <issue>Suppl 1</issue>
      <supplement>
        <named-content content-type="supplement-title">Abstracts from the 2014 Addiction Health Services Research (AHSR) Conference</named-content>
        <named-content content-type="supplement-sponsor">Synergy Inc. acted on behalf of the 2014 Addiction Health Services Research (AHSR) Conference in the preparation of this supplement. Synergy Inc. did not have any role (financial or non-financial) in the abstract selection process or the research itself, and was involved with the supplement on purely an administritive basis. Publication charges for this supplement were funded by the US National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA).</named-content>
      </supplement>
      <fpage>A34</fpage>
      <lpage>A34</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2015 Leukefeld et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Leukefeld et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.ascpjournal.org/content/10/S1/A34"/>
      <conference>
        <conf-date>15-17 October 2014</conf-date>
        <conf-name>2014 Addiction Health Services Research (AHSR) Conference</conf-name>
        <conf-loc>Boston, MA, USA</conf-loc>
      </conference>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Service organizational implementation trial</title>
      <p>The U.S. juvenile justice system has a number of possible behavioral health service community linkages for substance abuse and HIV services. However, there have only been a small number of systemic studies that examine and seek to improve these community behavioral health linkages for involved youth. Implementation science, as an emerging area, is a way of identifying, testing, and understanding effective strategies for translating treatment and prevention evidence-based approaches into community behavioral health service delivery. The purpose of this presentation, within the context of the Juvenile Justice-Translating Research Interventions for Adolescents in the Legal System (JJ-TRIALS) implementation behavioral health trial, is to describe the diverse settings in which the study will be initiated and how partners are involved in the study design. State partners include juvenile justice (JJ) and behavioral health services organizations in seven states (Florida, Georgia, Kentucky, Mississippi, New York, Pennsylvania, Texas) and the District of Columbia. Factors associated with selection, participation, and implementing the study in 36 sites will be explored. Each site will include a JJ agency and up to two community behavioral health service organizations for 7–10 implementation team members representing executive, management, supervisory, and line staff. JJ partner involvement is helping to design the study protocol that is both feasible for sites and meets partner needs. Study sites are defined as a county or service area, which can include multiple counties when behavioral health services are sparse. Site clusters will be used, which are defined within each state to assure that each of the six research centers have an equal number of experimental and control sites to take into account broader contextual factors. Options for defining clusters include county size, JJ youth population, urban/rural, or type of community supervision — probation or juvenile drug court. Sites will not be preselected for substance use or related behavioral health service needs, so youth are included with diverse behavioral health needs. Two JJ partners have actively participated on the study design work group, and the protocol has been vetted through partners at steering committee meetings and conference calls.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>The authors would like to acknowledge the contributions of JJ-TRIALS Juvenile Justice Partners for their efforts in developing all aspects of the study protocol. This work was supported by the National Institute on Drug Abuse.</p>
    </sec>
  </back>
</article>

