<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Addict Sci Clin Pract</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Addict Sci Clin Pract</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Addiction Science &amp; Clinical Practice</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1940-0632</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1940-0640</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4347501</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1940-0640-10-S1-A29</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1940-0640-10-S1-A29</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Meeting Abstract</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Designing the optimal JJ-TRIALS study: EPIS as a theoretical framework for selection and timing of implementation interventions</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1">
          <name>
            <surname>Knight</surname>
            <given-names>Danica</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>d.knight@tcu.edu</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2">
          <name>
            <surname>Belenko</surname>
            <given-names>Steven</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3">
          <name>
            <surname>Robertson</surname>
            <given-names>Angela</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4">
          <name>
            <surname>Wiley</surname>
            <given-names>Tisha</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A5">
          <name>
            <surname>Wasserman</surname>
            <given-names>Gail</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I5">5</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A6">
          <name>
            <surname>Leukefeld</surname>
            <given-names>Carl</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I6">6</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A7">
          <name>
            <surname>DiClemente</surname>
            <given-names>Ralph</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I7">7</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A8">
          <name>
            <surname>Brody</surname>
            <given-names>Gene</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I8">8</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A9">
          <name>
            <surname>Dennis</surname>
            <given-names>Michael</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I9">9</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A10">
          <name>
            <surname>Scott</surname>
            <given-names>Christy</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I10">10</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Institute of Behavioral Research, Texas Christian University, Fort Worth, TX, 76129, USA</aff>
      <aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Criminal Justice, Temple University, Philadelphia, PA, 19122, USA</aff>
      <aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Social Science Research Center, Mississippi State University, Starkville, MS, 39762, USA</aff>
      <aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Services Research Branch, National Institute on Drug Abuse, Rockville, MD, 20852, USA</aff>
      <aff id="I5"><label>5</label>Columbia University, New York, NY, 10027, USA</aff>
      <aff id="I6"><label>6</label>College of Medicine, University of Kentucky, Lexington, KY, 40506, USA</aff>
      <aff id="I7"><label>7</label>Center for AIDS Research, Emory University, Atlanta, GA, 30322, USA</aff>
      <aff id="I8"><label>8</label>Center for Family Research, University of Georgia, Athens, GA, 30602, USA</aff>
      <aff id="I9"><label>9</label>GAIN Coordinating Center, Chestnut Health Systems, Normal, IL, 61761, USA</aff>
      <aff id="I10"><label>10</label>Lighthouse Institute, Chestnut Health Systems, Chicago, IL, 60610, USA</aff>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>20</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>10</volume>
      <issue>Suppl 1</issue>
      <supplement>
        <named-content content-type="supplement-title">Abstracts from the 2014 Addiction Health Services Research (AHSR) Conference</named-content>
        <named-content content-type="supplement-sponsor">Synergy Inc. acted on behalf of the 2014 Addiction Health Services Research (AHSR) Conference in the preparation of this supplement. Synergy Inc. did not have any role (financial or non-financial) in the abstract selection process or the research itself, and was involved with the supplement on purely an administritive basis. Publication charges for this supplement were funded by the US National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA).</named-content>
      </supplement>
      <fpage>A29</fpage>
      <lpage>A29</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2015 Knight et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Knight et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.ascpjournal.org/content/10/S1/A29"/>
      <conference>
        <conf-date>15-17 October 2014</conf-date>
        <conf-name>2014 Addiction Health Services Research (AHSR) Conference</conf-name>
        <conf-loc>Boston, MA, USA</conf-loc>
      </conference>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title/>
      <p>Juvenile Justice-Translating Research Interventions for Adolescents in the Legal System (JJ-TRIALS; a cooperative implementation science initiative launched by NIDA in July 2013) seeks to reduce unmet substance use disorder (SUD) needs by assisting JJ agencies in their efforts to implement best practices and improve SUD service utilization along a behavioral health cascade (screening, assessment, referral, and treatment). Such efforts require systems-level change; thus, the JJ-TRIALS study targets JJ agencies and the behavioral health partners to which juveniles are referred (i.e., providers of SUD services).</p>
      <p>Aaron’s implementation science framework [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>] provides the foundation for study design and measurement. EPIS conceptualizes change processes as involving four phases: Exploration, Preparation, Implementation, and Sustainment (EPIS). The development of the implementation intervention components, the timing of components, and the measurement of process improvement activities are guided by Aarons’ EPIS model. For instance, data-driven decisionmaking (DDDM) templates and tools will provide basic support for goal selection during the Exploration phase. EPIS also has implications for measurement of process improvement activities. While the four phases are presented linearly, improvement activities may be somewhat recursive, with sites revisiting earlier phases when modifications in their action plans are needed (e.g., reworking Preparation plans after initial Implementation).</p>
      <p>Using a clustered randomized design, JJ-TRIALS will compare two implementation interventions: a Core Intervention, involving DDDM strategies to promote change across the EPIS phases, versus an Enhanced Intervention, providing support for DDDM through facilitation and inter-agency change teams. A total of 36 sites representing 7 states and the District of Columbia will be randomized to Core (n = 18) or Enhanced (n = 18) and to one of three start times. Primary research questions address whether DDDM strategies and facilitation of DDDM tools/implementation teams improve: a) the provision and quality of services along a behavioral health cascade (screening, assessment, referral, and treatment of youth with SUD); and b) attitudes toward/use of best practices among staff working with justice-involved youth. Exploratory research questions focus on aspects of the implementation process, inter-organizational collaboration, costs associated with each study arm, and youth outcomes.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>The authors would like to acknowledge the contributions of JJ-TRIALS Juvenile Justice Partners for their efforts in developing all aspects of the study protocol. This work was supported by the National Institute on Drug Abuse.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Aarons</surname>
            <given-names>GA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hurlburt</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Horwitz</surname>
            <given-names>SM</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Advancing a conceptual model of evidence-based practice implementation in public service sectors</article-title>
          <source>Administration and Policy in Mental Health and Mental Health Services Research</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>4</fpage>
          <lpage>23</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10488-010-0327-7</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21197565</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

