<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Ethnobiology and Ethnomedicine</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1746-4269</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25943542</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4449595</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">20</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13002-015-0020-8</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Ethnoveterinary practices of Covasna County, Transylvania, Romania</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Bartha</surname>
            <given-names>Sámuel Gergely</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>samuelgergely@gmail.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Quave</surname>
            <given-names>Cassandra L</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>cquave@emory.edu</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Balogh</surname>
            <given-names>Lajos</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>balogh.lajos@savariamuseum.hu</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Papp</surname>
            <given-names>Nóra</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>nora4595@gamma.ttk.pte.hu</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label/>Department of Pharmacognosy, University of Pécs, Rókus 2, Pécs, 7624 Hungary </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label/>Center for the Study of Human Health, Emory University, 550 Asbury Circle, Candler Library 107, Atlanta, GA 30322 USA </aff>
        <aff id="Aff3"><label/>Department of Dermatology, Emory University School of Medicine, 1518 Clifton Rd NE, CNR Bldg., Room 5035, Atlanta, GA 30322 USA </aff>
        <aff id="Aff4"><label/>Department of Natural History, Savaria Museum, Pf. 14, Szombathely, 9701 Hungary </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>6</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>6</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>11</volume>
      <elocation-id>35</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>13</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© Bartha et al.; licensee BioMed Central. 2015</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Ethnoveterinary medicine is a topic of growing interest among ethnobiologists, and is integral to the agricultural practices of many ethnic groups across the globe. The ethnoveterinary pharmacopoeia is often composed of ingredients available in the local environment, and may include plants, animals and minerals, or combinations thereof, for use in treating various ailments in reared animals. The aim of this study was to survey the current day ethnoveterinary practices of ethnic Hungarian (Székely) settlements situated in the Erdővidék commune (Covasna County, Transylvania, Romania) and to compare them with earlier works on this topic in Romania and other European countries.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>Data concerning ethnoveterinary practices were collected through semi-structured interviews and direct observation in 12 villages from 2010 to 2014. The cited plant species were collected, identified, dried and deposited in a herbarium. The use of other materials (e.g. animals, minerals and other substances) were also documented. Data were compared to earlier reports of ethnoveterinary knowledge in Transylvania and other European countries using various databases.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>In total, 26 wild and cultivated plants, 2 animals, and 17 other substances were documented to treat 11 ailments of cattle, horses, pigs, and sheep. The majority of applications were for the treatment of mastitis and skin ailments, while only a few data were reported for the treatment of cataracts, post-partum ailments and parasites. The traditional uses of <italic>Armoracia rusticana, Rumex</italic> spp., powdered sugar and glass were reported in each village. The use of some plant taxa, such as <italic>Allium sativum, Aristolochia clematitis</italic>, and <italic>Euphorbia amygdaloides</italic> was similar to earlier reports from other Transylvanian regions.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions</title>
          <p>Although permanent veterinary and medical services are available in some of the villages, elderly people preferred the use of wild and cultivated plants, animals and other materials in ethnoveterinary medicine. Some traditional ethnoveterinary practices are no longer in use, but rather persist only in the memories of the eldest subset of the population. A decline in the vertical transmission of ethnoveterinary knowledge was evident and loss of practice is likely compounded by market availability of ready-made pharmaceuticals.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Veterinary medicine</kwd>
        <kwd>Traditional knowledge</kwd>
        <kwd>Livestock</kwd>
        <kwd>Székelys</kwd>
        <kwd>Covasna</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>© The Author(s) 2015</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>The term “ethnoveterinary” refers to traditional therapeutics prepared by humans for the purposes of maintaining or restoring animal health. The ethnoveterinary pharmacopoeia often contains ingredients sourced from various locations within the environment, and may include plants, animals and minerals. Ethnoveterinary medicine dates back to ancient times and records of this practice can be found in various cultures across the globe. The study of ethnoveterinary medicine through a scientific lens began in the 1970s when it was defined by McCorkle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], and this subject encompasses theory, taxonomy, diagnosis, practice, resource, and social organization of the health of livestock and pets. Traditional curative and preventive treatments of domesticate and semi-domesticate animals play a significant role in several regions of the world where livestock is a main source of livelihood for rural peoples [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].</p>
      <p>In Romania, mostly in isolated settlements, several works have been published from the 1960s encompassing data on veterinary health problems of domesticated animals and their management [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Recently, declines in the transmission and implementation of traditional knowledge have been exacerbated by alteration and degradation of the environment, decreasing numbers of herds, and more expanded availability of officinal medicines and modern pharmaceuticals in several regions of the country. Nevertheless, several ethnic groups preserve the old traditions through home practices and oral transmission of knowledge.</p>
      <p>Covasna County, located in the eastern part of Transylvania (situated in central Romania) is inhabited by a population of ethnic Hungarians known as the Székelys. This ethnic group has lived in the Carpathian Basin since the 9th century.</p>
      <p>The flora of this area has been studied and published in valuable works [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Based on these descriptions, the region has a rich flora including relict and endemic species, as well as several medicinal plants used in traditional human and veterinary ethnomedicine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. In the summary of Rácz and Füzi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], medicinal plants were listed with local Hungarian, Romanian and scientific names, used part, village and amount of collection (kg/year). Their work highlights the decreasing occurrence of some wild species due to over-harvesting.</p>
      <p>Based on our previous ethnobotanical surveys [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>], the aim of this study was to document and analyze the ethnoveterinary practices of 12 settlements of the Erdővidék commune of Covasna County, Romania, focusing mainly on plant uses, common ailments and homemade therapeutics for livestock (e.g., cattle, horses, sheep and pigs). As no comparative fieldwork has been conducted on veterinary care in Covasna, our collected data were evaluated and compared to records of animal health management practices in Romania and other European countries.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="Sec3">
        <title>Study area</title>
        <p>Covasna County is located at elevations ranging from 460 to 1,777 m.a.s.l. in eastern Transylvania, situated in central Romania (longitude: 25°28’-26°28’, latitude: 45°32’-46°18’) (Figure <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The territory encompasses 3,705 km2. This region, which connects to the eastern part of the Carpathian Mountains, has been divided into four large zones: Baraolt Basin, Cîmpul Frumos, Superior Basin of Trei Scaune, Intorsura Buzăului and their surroundings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Erdővidék (“Timberland”) is found in the Baraolt Basin at the north-western part of the county, with a total area of 600 km<sc>2</sc>. The name “Timberland” comes from the territory being covered with forestland. Average temperatures vary from 2–7°C and the region has a precipitation of 500–1,100 mm per year [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. The rock-bed consists of vulcanian and sedimental elements. Due to the postvulcanian movement, about 150 mineral springs (“borvízforrás”) were discovered in the region, and are reputed for their medicinal effects. The geological relief of the region is diverse and comprises basins, mountains, valleys, plains and rivers (e.g. Olt, Kormos, Barót and Vargyas). The vegetation is also diverse and comprises beech, birch, hornbeam, oak, and pine forests, and alpine dwarf scrubland at different sea level. In total, the land use area of the county is divided into agriculture (48%), forestry (47.2%) and non-productive surfaces (4.8%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>].<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Map of the study sites in Covasna County, Romania [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. Image adapted from Google Earth (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://earth.google.com/">https://earth.google.com/</ext-link>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13002_2015_20_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
        <p>A 2009 population survey reported the presence of 8,600 ethnic Hungarians (Székely) distributed across 23 villages in Erdővidék [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. The following settlements were selected in our study: Aita Seacă (in Hungarian: Szárazajta), Băţanii Mari (Nagybacon), Băţanii Mici (Kisbacon), Biborţeni (Bibarcfalva), <italic>Bodoş</italic> (Bodos), Filia (Erdőfüle), Herculian (Magyarhermány), Ozunca-Băi (Uzonkafürdő), Racoşul de Sus (Felsőrákos), Tălişoara (Olasztelek), Valea Zălanului (Zalánpatak), and Vârghiş (Vargyas) (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, Figure <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>
<bold>Study sites in Covasna County, Romania</bold>
</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr valign="top"><th>
<bold>Study area</bold>
</th><th>
<bold>Latitude</bold>
</th><th>
<bold>Longitude</bold>
</th><th>
<bold>Informants/Inhabitants [</bold>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
<bold>]</bold>
</th><th>
<bold>Medical service</bold>
</th><th>
<bold>Veterinary practice</bold>
</th><th>
<bold>Pharmacy</bold>
</th><th>
<bold>Local features [</bold>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>
<bold>]</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="top"><td>Aita Seacă</td><td>46° 02′ 17″</td><td>25° 41′ 23″</td><td>7/782</td><td>─*</td><td>─</td><td>─</td><td>saline fountain</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Băţanii Mari</td><td>46° 05′ 22″</td><td>25° 41′ 29″</td><td>15/1936</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>─</td><td>mineral springs</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Băţanii Mici</td><td>46° 06′ 13″</td><td>25° 41′ 42″</td><td>8/558</td><td>─*</td><td>─</td><td>─</td><td>mineral springs</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Biborţeni</td><td>46° 05′ 37″</td><td>25° 39′ 22″</td><td>5/775</td><td>+</td><td>─</td><td>+</td><td>mineral springs</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Bodos</td><td>46° 04′ 34″</td><td>25° 39′ 36″</td><td>9/446</td><td>─</td><td>─</td><td>─</td><td>charcoal-burner (“baksa”)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Filia</td><td>46° 08′ 38″</td><td>25° 37′ 17″</td><td>8/1240</td><td>+</td><td>─</td><td>+</td><td>iron forge, wooden headbords in the cemetery</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Herculian</td><td>46° 08′ 02″</td><td>25° 42′ 35″</td><td>7/1168</td><td>+</td><td>─</td><td>+</td><td>mineral springs</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Ozunca-Băi</td><td>46° 06′ 20″</td><td>25° 47′ 20″</td><td>3/54</td><td>─</td><td>─</td><td>─</td><td>mineral springs, medicinal bath</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Racoşul de Sus</td><td>46° 04′ 45″</td><td>25° 32′ 53″</td><td>6/893</td><td>─ *</td><td>─</td><td>─</td><td>mineral springs</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Tălişoara</td><td>46° 06′ 18″</td><td>25° 35′ 19″</td><td>5/743</td><td>─</td><td>─</td><td>─</td><td>mineral springs</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Valea Zălanului</td><td>46° 00′ 40″</td><td>25° 45′ 22″</td><td>12/149</td><td>─</td><td>─</td><td>─</td><td>mineral springs</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Vârghiş</td><td>46° 07′ 41″</td><td>25° 33′ 25″</td><td>14/1647</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>mineral springs</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<italic>*Aita Seacă, Băţanii Mici, Racoşul de Sus:</italic> no permanent medical service; temporary medical service is available twice per week from from neighbouring communities.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
        <p>Native people of the county speak Romanian and Hungarian, while in the selected villages the predominant language is Hungarian. The majority of villagers were born in the area and have lived there for most of their lifetime. Many are engaged in traditional agricultural and pastoral activities, working as farmers, ranchers and shepherds. Cattle, goats, horse, sheep and pigs are commonly raised in farms and around the home. They continue to play a key role in the production of dairy products and other traditional foods in the district, as has been the case for centuries. Although some of these villages have access to allopathic medical and veterinary care, as well as access to pharmaceutical drugs (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), most people know of several home treatments for veterinary health problems using materials of various origins.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec4">
        <title>Field work and data collection</title>
        <p>Field studies were carried out in the summers of 2010–2014. A total of 99 informants were asked with snow-ball technique in semi-structured interviews in Hungarian. Prior informed consent was obtained prior to conducting interviews and all researchers adhered to the ethical guidelines of the International Society of Ethnobiology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. During interviews, details concerning common ailments of domesticated animals, ingredients to traditional therapies (coming from plant, animal, and mineral origin) as well as local healing methods were recorded. Informants were followed into the local agro-ecosytem (e.g. fields, meadows, pastures, ploughlands and road-sides) surrounding villages in order to show and gather the cited wild and cultivated plants (Figure <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Regarding the cited plant taxa, data concerning the following topics were collected: local name(s), frequency, habitat, time of collection, method of storage, used part, preparation, category and way of use, treated ailments and animals with local name(s), possible beliefs and rituals. Interviews were documented with tape recordings and photos were taken of plants and their habitat as well as the final therapeutic products. Voucher specimens of the cited plants were prepared and deposited at the Department of Pharmacognosy of the University of Pécs. Scientific nomenclature of for botanical taxa followed the systematic work of Tutin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>].<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>A shepherd works with his livestock in Ozunca-Băi.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13002_2015_20_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec5">
        <title>Data analysis</title>
        <p>A search for ethnoveterinary studies in some major databases was conducted and the data collected in this study was compared to earlier documented records in Transylvania and other European countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. During comparison, similarity and differences of the records were taken into consideration.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec6" sec-type="results">
      <title>Results and discussion</title>
      <p>There are several small private herds widespread in the county. People keep fewer livestock nowadays than in the past, which has resulted in a significant decrease the number of cattle herds. In addition, the prevalence and increased use of agricultural mechanization has led to the reduction in the number of horses necessary for agricultural activities. Nevertheless, domesticated animals continue to play an important role in their everyday life in the region.</p>
      <p>Among the 99 informants (63 women and 36 men) aged between 27 and 99 years, only 75 villagers reported that they currently raise cattle, horses, sheep or pigs and use ethnoveterinary treatments. While the other 24 informants do not currently rear livestock, they did in the past and where able to provide information regarding past ethnoveterinary practices used during their lifetime. Declines in the transmission of traditional ethnoveterinary knowledge are apparent, and is likely linked to emigration trends among young people seeking employment in larger cities and even foreign countries. In addition, many informants commented on a sense of greater faith in modern veterinary medicines prescribed by veterinarians than their own home remedies.</p>
      <p>Altogether, 11 ailments reported to be most frequently treated via ethnoveterinary means (Tables <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>,<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>,<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Among the cited ailments, “hotness” (stomach disorders), inflamed udder (mastitis), respiratory diseases (roaring = “kehesség”, infectious cold, cough, pneumonia), rumination disorders, wounds and skin injuries, diarrhea, and cataracts were listed, and local methods were also used in post-partum therapies and as anthelmintic, diuretic, antiparasitic, repellent and insecticide drugs. The majority of ethnoveterinary therapeutics were observed to treat the ailments of cattle (48 records), while 26 remedies were mentioned for horses, 15 for pigs, and 5 for sheep.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>
<bold>Plant taxa used in ethnoveterinary medicine of the selected villages</bold>
</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr valign="top"><th>
<bold>Used plants and voucher code</bold>
</th><th>
<bold>Family</bold>
</th><th>
<bold>Local name</bold>
</th><th>
<bold>Medicinal use</bold>
</th><th>
<bold>Status</bold>
<sup><bold>*</bold></sup>
</th><th>
<bold>Number of citations</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="top"><td>
<italic>Achillea millefolium</italic> L. (EV-03)</td><td>Asteraceae</td><td>
<italic>cickafarok, cickafarkkóró, pulykafű, egérfarkú virág, egérfarkúfű, egérfarkúfűvirág</italic>
</td><td>herb as a tea for rumination [cattle]</td><td>W</td><td>3</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>
<italic>Allium sativum</italic> L. (EV-22)</td><td>Amaryllidaceae</td><td>fokhagyma</td><td>bulb for anthelmintics [pig]</td><td>C</td><td>76</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>
<italic>Aristolochia clematitis</italic> L. (EV-23)</td><td>Aristolochiaceae</td><td>farkasalma</td><td>leaf for wounds and skin injuries [cattle, horse, pig, sheep]</td><td>W</td><td>54</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>
<italic>Armoracia rusticana</italic> G. Gaertn., B. Mey. &amp; Schreb. (EV-11)</td><td>Brassicaceae</td><td>torma</td><td>root for respiratory disorders [horse]</td><td>C</td><td>71</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="2">
<italic>Artemisia absinthium</italic> L. (EV-13)</td><td rowspan="2">Asteraceae</td><td rowspan="2">
<italic>üröm,</italic> fehér üröm</td><td>herb for stomach heat, inflammation, and ache [cattle]</td><td rowspan="2">W</td><td>4</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>for diarrhea [cattle, horse]</td><td>5</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>
<italic>Calendula officinalis</italic> L. (EV-12)</td><td>Asteraceae</td><td>
<italic>sárgavirág</italic>
</td><td>flower as a cream for inflamed udder and mastitis [cattle]</td><td>C</td><td>4</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="2">
<italic>Cucurbita pepo</italic> L. (EV-21)</td><td rowspan="2">Cucurbitaceae</td><td rowspan="2">tök</td><td>ground seed and seed oil for rumination [cattle]</td><td rowspan="2">C</td><td>3</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>for anthelmintics [pig]</td><td>2</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>
<italic>Daucus carota</italic> L. subsp. <italic>sativus</italic> Hoffm. (EV-04)</td><td>Apiaceae</td><td>
<italic>murok</italic>
</td><td>root for anthelmintics [horse]</td><td>C</td><td>4</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>
<italic>Eryngium planum</italic> L. (EV-17)</td><td>Apiaceae</td><td>
<italic>kék tilinkó, szamárcsipke, bojtorján</italic>
</td><td>herb for inflamed udder and mastitis [cattle, horse]</td><td>W</td><td>7</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>
<italic>Euphorbia amygdaloides</italic> L. (EV-01)</td><td>Euphorbiaceae</td><td>
<italic>árió</italic>
</td><td>herb for wounds and skin injuries [horse, pig]</td><td>W</td><td>6</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>
<italic>Gentiana asclepiadea</italic> L. (EV-15)</td><td>Gentianaceae</td><td>
<italic>gyertyagyökerű, gyertyagyükerű, sárgagyökér</italic>
</td><td>root as a tea for stomach heat, inflammation, and ache [cattle]</td><td>W</td><td>4</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>
<italic>Juglans regia</italic> L. (EV-16)</td><td>Juglandaceae</td><td>dió</td><td>leaf against flies as a rub [horse]</td><td>C</td><td>47</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>
<italic>Juniperus communis</italic> L. (EV-14)</td><td>Cupressaceae</td><td>
<italic>borsika</italic>
</td><td>pseudofruit for respiratory disorders [horse]</td><td>W</td><td>6</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>
<italic>Matricaria chamomilla</italic> L. (EV-10)</td><td>Asteraceae</td><td>
<italic>kamillavirág</italic>
</td><td>flower as a tea and wash for inflamed udder and mastitis [cattle]</td><td>W</td><td>11</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="2">
<italic>Petroselinum crispum</italic> (Mill.) Fuss (EV-09)</td><td rowspan="2">Apiaceae</td><td rowspan="2">
<italic>ződ peterzselyem</italic>
</td><td>leaf for rumination and after delivery [cattle]</td><td rowspan="2">C</td><td>9</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>for diuretics [horse]</td><td>5</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>
<italic>Plantago lanceolata</italic> L. (EV-25)</td><td>Plantaginaceae</td><td>
<italic>kígyónyelvűfű hegyesútilapi, kígyónyelvű útifű, keskeny útifű lándzsás/keskeny útilapi</italic>
</td><td>leaf for stomach heat, inflammation, and ache [cattle]</td><td>W</td><td>12</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>
<italic>Polygonum minus</italic> Huds. (EV-02)</td><td>Polygonaceae</td><td>
<italic>árió, veresszárúfű</italic>
</td><td>herb as a washing for wounds and skin injuries [cattle, horse]</td><td>W</td><td>11</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>
<italic>Potentilla anserina</italic> L. (EV-05)</td><td>Rosaceae</td><td>
<italic>pipefű, lúdlábfű, lúdfű</italic>
</td><td>leaf for diarrhea [cattle, horse, pig, sheep]</td><td>W</td><td>71</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="2">
<italic>Quercus petraea</italic> (Matt.) Liebl.<break/>(EV-19)</td><td rowspan="2">Fagaceae</td><td rowspan="2">
<italic>cserefa, cseremakk, cserháncs</italic>
</td><td>nut for anthelmintics [pig, cattle]</td><td rowspan="2">W</td><td>4</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>young bark as a tea for diarrhea [pig]</td><td>5</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="2">
<italic>Quercus robur</italic> L. (EV-20)</td><td rowspan="2">Fagaceae</td><td rowspan="2">
<italic>cserefa, cseremakk, cserháncs</italic>
</td><td>nut for anthelmintics [pig, cattle]</td><td rowspan="2">W</td><td>4</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>young bark as a tea for diarrhea [pig]</td><td>5</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>
<italic>Rumex acetosella</italic> L. (EV-07)</td><td>Polygonaceae</td><td>
<italic>lósósdi, lósóska</italic>
</td><td>fruit for diarrhea [cattle, horse, pig, sheep]</td><td>W</td><td>75</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>
<italic>Rumex obtusifolius</italic> L. (EV-06)</td><td>Polygonaceae</td><td>
<italic>lósósdi, lósóska</italic>
</td><td>fruit for diarrhea [cattle, horse, pig, sheep]</td><td>W</td><td>75</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>
<italic>Salix alba</italic> L. (EV-24)</td><td>Salicaceae</td><td>fűzfa</td><td>leaf as fodder for stomach heat, ache, inflammation, and rumination, leafy branches and bark for rumination [cattle]</td><td>W</td><td>24</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>
<italic>Secale cereale</italic> L. (EV-26)</td><td>Poaceae</td><td>rozs</td><td>fruit for anthelmintics [horse]</td><td>C</td><td>4</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>
<italic>Symphytum officinale</italic> L. (EV-18)</td><td>Boraginaceae</td><td>
<italic>fekete nadály, nadály, forrasztófű</italic>
</td><td>root with bran for rumination [cattle]</td><td>W</td><td>5</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>
<italic>Veratrum album</italic> L. (EV-08)</td><td>Melanthiaceae</td><td>
<italic>ászpa,</italic> (fehér)zászpa</td><td>ground root as a rub against lice [horse]</td><td>W</td><td>5</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<sup><bold>*</bold></sup>
<italic>Status:</italic> W = growing in wild habitat; C = cultivated in gardens.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>
<bold>Animals and other materials used in ethnoveterinary medicine of the study area</bold>
</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr valign="top"><th>
<bold>Animals</bold>
</th><th>
<bold>Medicinal use</bold>
</th><th>
<bold>Number of citations</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="top"><td>
<italic>Menyet</italic> (<italic>Mustela nivalis</italic> L.)</td><td>skin as an embrocation by itself or soaked in milk for mastitis [cattle]</td><td>29</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Tetű (lices)</td><td>put into the urethra as a diuretic [horse]</td><td>3</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>
<bold>Minerals and other substances</bold>
</td><td/><td>
<bold>Number of citations</bold>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Bread</td><td>for rumination [cattle]</td><td>11</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Clay</td><td>by itself or with salt as an embrocation for mastitis [cattle]</td><td>9</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Cobweb</td><td>as an embrocation for skin injuries [horse]</td><td>3</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>“hótszén” (hot embers quenched in water)</td><td>for diarrhea [pig]</td><td>4</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Glass (powdered)</td><td>blown into the eyes for cataract [cattle]</td><td>63</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>“szénamurha” (hay)</td><td>by itself or poured with urine for respiratory diseases [horse]</td><td>31</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Injection</td><td>for respiratory diseases [horse]</td><td>3</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Milk</td><td>for stomach heat, inflammation, ache [cattle], with <italic>Allium sativum</italic> as an anthelmintic [pig]</td><td>22</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Oil</td><td>for stomach heat, inflammation, ache, rumination [cattle]</td><td>25</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Salt</td><td>with water and vinegar as a wash or embrocation for mastitis [cattle]</td><td>7</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Sugar (powdered)</td><td>blown into the eyes for cataract [cattle]</td><td>61</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Turpentine</td><td>for respiratory diseases [horse]</td><td>2</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Toast</td><td>for rumination [cattle]</td><td>9</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Urine (human)</td><td>poured onto “szénamurha” for respiratory diseases [horse]</td><td>5</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Vinegar</td><td>with water and salt as a wash or embrocation for mastitis [cattle]</td><td>18</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="3">Water</td><td>with vinegar and salt as a wash or embrocation for mastitis [cattle]</td><td>19</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>poured beside the animals as a diuretic [horse]</td><td>7</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>put into the shed to vaporize and induce urination [sheep]</td><td>6</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Whey powder</td><td>anthelmintics [pig]</td><td>3</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>
<bold>Ethnoveterinary practices in the study area compared with earlier records in Romania and some European countries</bold>
</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr valign="top"><th>
<bold>Diseases treated in ethnoveterinary practice</bold>
</th><th colspan="2">
<bold>Ethnomedicinal treatments in the studied villages</bold>
<sup><bold>*</bold></sup>
</th><th colspan="2">
<bold>Earlier reported data in Romania</bold>
</th><th colspan="2">
<bold>Data in other countries</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="top"><td/><td>Used ingredients</td><td>Parts used and preparation</td><td>Used ingredients</td><td>Parts used and preparation</td><td>Used ingredients</td><td>Parts used and preparation</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>“hotness” (stomach heat, inflammation, ache)</td><td>
<italic>Artemisia absinthium</italic>
</td><td>herb<sup>1,4</sup> [cattle]</td><td>
<italic>Centaurium erythraea</italic> Rafn. (Gentianaceae)</td><td>herb as tea [pig] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Achillea millefolium</italic>
</td><td>flowers as infusion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>
<italic>Plantago lanceolata</italic>
</td><td>leaf with the herb of <italic>A. absinthium</italic>
<sup>1</sup> [cattle]</td><td>
<italic>Levisticum officinale</italic> W.D.J. Koch (Apiaceae)</td><td>herb with rancid pork fat and bitter salt [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Matricaria chamomilla</italic>
</td><td>flowers as infusion [calves] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>
<italic>Gentiana asclepiadea</italic> (Figure <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>)</td><td>root with <italic>P. lanceolata</italic> as a tea<sup>12</sup> [cattle]</td><td>
<italic>Peucedanum oreoselinum</italic> Moench (Apiaceae)</td><td>herb as fodder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Potentilla erecta</italic> (L.) Raeusch. (Rosaceae)</td><td>root as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>
<italic>Salix alba</italic>
</td><td>leaf as fodder<sup>12</sup> [cattle]</td><td>
<italic>Rumex crispus</italic> L. (Polygonaceae)</td><td>seed soaked in brandy for digestive problems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]</td><td>milk</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>milk</td><td>[cattle]<sup>5</sup>
</td><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>oil</td><td>[cattle]<sup>5,9</sup>
</td><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td>inflamed udder, mastitis</td><td>
<italic>Calendula officinalis</italic>
</td><td>flower as a cream<sup>2</sup> [cattle, horse]</td><td>
<italic>Brassica oleracea</italic>
</td><td>sour leaf sap with human urine and dung of horse as a cream [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Brassica oleracea</italic>
</td><td>roasted leaf as an embrocation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>
<italic>Eryngium planum</italic>
</td><td>herb as a tea<sup>2</sup> or washing<sup>12</sup> [cattle, horse]</td><td>
<italic>Calendula officinalis</italic>
</td><td>flower as a cream [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Calamintha nepeta</italic> (L.) Savi (Lamiaceae)</td><td>leaf as a wash [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>
<italic>Matricaria chamomilla</italic>
</td><td>flower as a tea and wash<sup>12</sup> [cattle]</td><td>
<italic>Digitalis grandiflora</italic> Mill. (Plantaginaceae)</td><td>herb [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Malus sylvestris</italic> (L.) Mill. (Rosaceae)</td><td>cider vinegar of fruit with grain as fodder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>
<italic>Mustela nivalis</italic>
</td><td>skin as an embrocation by itself<sup>2,6,9,11</sup> or soaked in milk<sup>7</sup> [cattle]</td><td>
<italic>Malus sylvestris</italic>
</td><td>vinegar of fruit on slate as impregnant, as an embrocation [cattle] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Malva sylvestris</italic>
</td><td>fresh leaf boiled and placed into sack using as a warm compress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>cold water</td><td>as a wash<sup>1,2,6,12</sup>; with vinegar<sup>2,3</sup> and salt<sup>7</sup> as a wash<sup>2,7</sup> or embrocation<sup>3</sup> [cattle]</td><td>
<italic>Mustela nivalis</italic>
</td><td>as a rubber [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Olea europaea</italic> L. var. <italic>europaea</italic> (Oleaceae)</td><td>fruit as an ointment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>clay</td><td>by itself or with salt as an embrocation<sup>7</sup> [cattle]</td><td>
<italic>Papaver somniferum</italic> L. (Papaveraceae)</td><td>seed as fodder for “reszfug” (= mastitis) [cattle, sheep] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Sambucus nigra</italic> L. (Adoxaceae)</td><td>flower in fumigation [cattle] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Scrophularia nodosa</italic> L., <italic>részfugburján</italic> (Scrophulariaceae)</td><td>as a wash [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>], mixed and cooked with salt and flour of <italic>Zea mays</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] dried and mixed into the flour as fodder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> L. (Lamiaceae)</td><td>decoction of flowering stem as a wash [cattle, dog, sheep] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Picea abies</italic> (L.) H. Karst. (Pinaceae)</td><td>resin by itself, or with sour cream or tallow as an embrocation [Papp, unpublished data, Uz-valley]</td><td>
<italic>Zea mays</italic> L. (Poaceae)</td><td>seed as a decoction in water and/or milk as a washing [cattle] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>flour</td><td>with salt [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>water</td><td>with vinegar and salt as a washing and an embrocation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>yellow mud</td><td>smeared onto the udder [cattle] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td>respiratory diseases: roaring (“kehesség”), cold, cough, pneumonia</td><td>
<italic>Armoracia rusticana</italic>
</td><td>root as fodder<sup>1–12</sup> [horse]</td><td>
<italic>Allium cepa</italic> L. (Amaryllidaceae)</td><td>3 slices of the bulb grated and soaked in brandy, and mixed with saltpetre [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Allium cepa</italic>
</td><td>bulb [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Armoracia rusticana</italic>
</td><td>root by itself [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>], or with <italic>Avena sativa</italic> and urine for “száraz kehe” (dry cough) of horse [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], or in boiled milk with one spoon of honey, tallow, yeast, 7 slices of <italic>Allium sativum</italic>, and 9 fruits of <italic>Pimenta dioica</italic> (L.) Merr., Myrtaceae and <italic>Syzygium aromaticum</italic> (L.) Merr. &amp; L.M. Perry, Myrtaceae and <italic>Piper nigrum</italic> L., Pipeaceae [horse] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], or with “büdöskővirág” (sulphur powder) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Atropa belladonna</italic> L. (Solanaceae)</td><td>leaf [horse, dog] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>
<italic>Juniperus communis</italic>
</td><td>pseudofruit as fodder<sup>7</sup> [horse]</td><td>
<italic>Avena sativa</italic> L., Poaceae</td><td>warmed by itself [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], or with urine, turpentine or “büdöskővirág” put into a sac and pull onto the head of horse as a steaming</td><td>
<italic>Avena sativa</italic>
</td><td>aerial part [horse] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>injection</td><td>[horse] <sup>1</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Brassica oleracea</italic>
</td><td>leaf sap dropped into the nostrils with dried and ground rat snake [horse] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Eucalyptus globulus</italic> Labill. (Myrtaceae)</td><td>leaf [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>“szénamurha”</td><td>by itself<sup>1,5,12</sup> or poured with urine<sup>7</sup> [horse]</td><td>
<italic>Datura stramonium</italic> L. (Solanaceae)</td><td>leaf [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Helleborus bocconei</italic> Ten. (Ranunculaceae)</td><td>petiole inserted into the ear or the neck for bronchitis [cattle] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>turpentine</td><td>[horse]<sup>1</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Helleborus purpurascens</italic> Waldst. &amp; Kit. (Ranunculaceae)</td><td>leaf soaked in whey [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], or pulled into the breast [horse, cow], and into the ears [pig] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>] for dry and purulent cough [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Helleborus foetidus</italic> L. (Ranunculaceae) [cattle][<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]</td><td>leaf inserted into the ears for bronchitis and pneumonia [cattle] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> L., <italic>H. vulgare</italic> convar. <italic>vulgare</italic> (Poaceae)</td><td>steaming with warmed seed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>], flour with honey and water [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Juniperus phoenicea</italic> L. (Cupressaceae)</td><td>leaf [cattle, sheep, dog, horse] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Juniperus communis</italic>
</td><td>as a tea [horse] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Mercurialis annua</italic> L. (Euphorbiaceae)</td><td>root as a tea [dog] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Levisticum officinale</italic> W.D.J. Koch (Apiaceae)</td><td>aerial part as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Origanum heracleoticum</italic> L. (Lamiaceae)</td><td>aerial part [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Matricaria chamomilla</italic>
</td><td>flower as a tea [pig] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td><td>Sugar</td><td>on hot coal as a fumigant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Malus sylvestris</italic>
</td><td>vinegar of the fruit as an embrocation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td><td>tin</td><td>melted and inserted into the nose [horse] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Pulmonaria officinalis</italic> L. (Boraginaceae)</td><td>flower for pneumonia [pig] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Secale cereale</italic> L. (Poaceae)</td><td>flour for “fojókehe” for steaming [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L. (Poaceae)</td><td>bran by itself [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>bear, goose and pork fat</td><td>for “csikókehe, fojtókehe” [horse] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>salt</td><td>sprinkled onto the nose [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>sulphur powder</td><td>for “csikókehe, fojtókehe” [horse] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>venesection</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td>rumination</td><td>
<italic>Achillea millefolium</italic>
</td><td>herb as a tea [cattle]<sup>12</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Allium sativum</italic>
</td><td>bulb with bread [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], or with wine and egg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Achillea millefolium</italic>
</td><td>aerial part [cattle] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>
<italic>Cucurbita pepo</italic>
</td><td>ground seed and seed oil [cattle]<sup>2</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Angelica sylvestris</italic> L. (Apiaceae)</td><td>leaf [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Artemisia absinthium</italic>
</td><td>aerial part as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>
<italic>Petroselinum crispum</italic>
</td><td>leaf [cattle]<sup>2</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Armoracia rusticana</italic>
</td><td>roasted fruit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Pimpinella anisum</italic> L. (Apiaceae)</td><td>fruit as an elixir [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>
<italic>Salix alba</italic>
</td><td>leaf, leafy branches and bark [cattle]<sup>3</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Artemisia dracunculus</italic>
</td><td>herb as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Ruta chalepensis</italic> L. (Rutaceae)</td><td>aerial part as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>
<italic>Symphytum officinale</italic> L.</td><td>root as fodder with bran [cattle]<sup>12</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Avena sativa</italic>
</td><td>roasted fruit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Salix purpurea</italic> L., (Salicaceae)</td><td>branches [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>bread</td><td>[cattle]<sup>3,4</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Beta vulgaris</italic> L. convar. <italic>crassa</italic> (Amaranthaceae)</td><td>grated root [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Tanacetum parthenium</italic> (L.) Schultz Bip. (Asteraceae)</td><td>aerial part as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>Toast</td><td>[cattle] <sup>7</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Cannabis sativa</italic> L. (Cannabaceae)</td><td>seed in oil [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td>Beer</td><td>[cattle] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>Oil</td><td>[cattle] <sup>7</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Carum carvi</italic> L. (Apiaceae)</td><td>fruit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</td><td>Buttermilk</td><td>[cattle] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Cucurbita maxima</italic> Duchesne (Cucurbitaceae)</td><td>seed with bran [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]</td><td>soda (sodium bicarbonate)</td><td>[cattle] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Cucurbita pepo</italic>
</td><td>ground seed with milk [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]</td><td>whey</td><td>[cattle] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Daucus carota</italic> ssp. <italic>sativus</italic> Hoffm.</td><td>root [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Euonymus europaeus</italic> L. (Celastraceae)</td><td>fruit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Equisetum sylvaticum</italic> L. (Equisetaceae)</td><td>herb [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Fragaria vesca</italic> L. (Rosaceae)</td><td>fruit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] or root as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Helianthus annuus</italic> L. (Asteraceae)</td><td>pressed seed coat [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Iris germanica</italic> L. (Iridaceae)</td><td>root [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Juniperus communis</italic>
</td><td>pseudofruit with milk, roasted on bread [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], or woth the leaf of <italic>Salix alba</italic>, rusty fat, oil and bulb of <italic>Allium cepa</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Levisticum officinale</italic> W.D.J. Koch (Apiaceae)</td><td>herb [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Linum usitatissimum</italic> L. (Linaceae)</td><td>seed as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>L. usitatissimum</italic> convar. <italic>Transitorium</italic> (Linaceae)</td><td>ground seed with the seed of <italic>Helianthus annuus</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Malus domestica</italic> Borkh.</td><td>vinegar with yeast and <italic>Artemisia dracunculus</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Matricaria chamomilla</italic>
</td><td>flower as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Petroselinum crispum</italic>
</td><td>leaf with bran and oil [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Peucedanum oreoselinum</italic> Moench (Apiaceae)</td><td>herb [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Prunus domestica</italic> L. ssp<italic>. Rotunda</italic> (Rosaceae)</td><td>leafy branches [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Raphanus sativus</italic> L. cv. <italic>niger</italic> f. s<italic>ubglobosa</italic> (Brassicaceae)</td><td>tuber [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>], or with cooking soda [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Rumex stenophyllus</italic> Ledeb.(Polygonaceae)</td><td>herb [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Rubus idaeus</italic> L. convar. <italic>hortensis</italic> provar. <italic>inermis</italic> (Rosaceae)</td><td>fruit as a syrup [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Sambucus nigra</italic>
</td><td>lower layer of the bark [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Salix alba</italic>
</td><td>leafy branches [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Salix</italic> spp.</td><td>leafy branches [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Satureja hortensis</italic> L. (Lamiaceae)</td><td>herb [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Sisymbrium strictissimum</italic> L. (Brassicaceae)</td><td>root [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>
</td><td>fruit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Zea mays</italic>
</td><td>stem [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>copper sulphate</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>white wine</td><td>with egg [sheep] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td>wounds, skin injuries</td><td>
<italic>Aristolochia clematitis</italic>
</td><td>leaf as an embrocation [cattle, horse, pig, sheep]<sup>1,2,4,6–11</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Achillea millefolium</italic>
</td><td>herb cut and mixed with rancid fat [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Acer pseudoplatanus</italic> L. (Sapindaceae)</td><td>decoction of the bark as a wash [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>
<italic>Eryngium planum</italic>
</td><td>herb as a tea [cattle, horse]<sup>2</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Aristolochia clematitis</italic>
</td><td>decoction of the stem and leaf as a wash, or the leaf as an embrocation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Althaea officinalis</italic> L. (Malvaceae)</td><td>root [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>
<italic>Euphorbia amygdaloides</italic>
</td><td>herb as a tea [horse, pig]<sup>12</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Betula pendula</italic> Roth. (Betulaceae)</td><td>leaf for bruised skin (“pecsendzsia, pokolszökés”) as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Agave americana</italic> L. (Asparagaceae)</td><td>leaf [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>
<italic>Polygonum minus</italic>
</td><td>as a washing [cattle, horse]<sup>10</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Chelidonium majus</italic> L. (Papaveraceae)</td><td>leaf sap [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Artemisia absinthium</italic>
</td><td>aerial part with honey [horse] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>cobweb</td><td>as an embrocation [horse]<sup>5</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Crataegus monogyna</italic> Jacq. (Rosaceae)</td><td>fruit or leafy branches as a decoction [ox] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Bovista dermoxantha</italic> Pers. (Lycoperdaceae)</td><td>old fruiting body [horse] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Daphne mezereum</italic> L. (Thymelaeaceae)</td><td>bark [sheep] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], flower as an infusion [horse] [Papp, unpublished data, Uz-valley]</td><td>
<italic>Cardopatum corymbosum</italic> (L.) Pers. (Asteraceae)</td><td>leaf [sheep,cattle, dog] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Euphorbia amygdaloides</italic> (Euphorbiaceae)</td><td>ground herb ss an embrocation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>], or as a wash ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>] Papp, unpublished data, Uz-valley)</td><td>
<italic>Carpinus orientalis</italic> Mill. (Betulaceaeae)</td><td>bark as a decoction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Euphorbia cyparissias</italic> (Euphorbiaceae)</td><td>herb as a wash [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Centaurea alba</italic> L. ssp. <italic>tartesiana</italic> Talavera (Asteraceae)</td><td>leaf [horse] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Euphorbia palustris</italic> L. (Euphorbiaceae)</td><td>herb as a wash [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Daphne gnidium</italic> L. (Thymelaeaceae)</td><td>stem as a liniment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Polygonum lapathifolium</italic> L. (Polygonaceae)</td><td>leaf as an embrocation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Ecballium elaterium</italic> (L.) A. Rich. (Cucurbitaceae)</td><td>fruit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Symphytum officinale</italic>
</td><td>root [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Euphorbia hirsuta</italic> L. (Euphorbiaceae)</td><td>[sheep, cattle, horse, dog] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Veronica beccabunga</italic> L. (Plantaginaceae)</td><td>herb as a wash [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Gentiana lutea</italic> L. (Gentianaceae)</td><td>root as a bath [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>cobweb</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Geranium rotundifolium</italic> L. (Geraniaceae)</td><td>aerial part [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>hot fat</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Hypericum perforatum</italic>
</td><td>aerial part [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>lime</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Juniperus oxycedrus</italic> L. (Cupressaceae)</td><td>pseudofruit as an ointment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>urine</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Lilium pyrenaicum</italic> Gouan (Liliaceae)</td><td>bulb as a liniment and a poultice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Malva neglecta</italic> Wallr. (Malvaceae)</td><td>aerial part [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], leaf [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Marrubium vulgare</italic> L. (Lamiaceae)</td><td>aerial part [sheep, cattle] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic> L. (Solanaceae)</td><td>leaf [sheep] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Peucedanum ostruthium</italic> (L.) W.D.J.Koch (Apiaceae)</td><td>root as an ointment and bath [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Prunus domestica</italic>
</td><td>fruit by itself [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], or in fermented and distilled form [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Pulicaria odora</italic> Rchb. (Asteraceae)</td><td>flowering top in alcohol or as a decoction [cattle, sheep, dog, horse] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Quercus ilex</italic> L. ssp. <italic>ilex</italic>, <italic>Q. petraea</italic> (Matt.) Liebl. (Fagaceae)</td><td>bark as a bath [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Ruta chalepensis</italic>
</td><td>aerial part as an embrocation and liniment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Sambucus nigra</italic>
</td><td>leaf as a decoction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Symphytum officinale</italic>
</td><td>root as an ointment and bath [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Valeriana officinalis</italic> L. (Caprifoliaceae)</td><td>root or leaf in mules [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>fat</td><td>fox fat for pimples [horse], hen fat for sores [oxen] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>Sulphur</td><td>in water for burns [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>Cobweb</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>anthelmintics</td><td>
<italic>Allium sativum</italic>
</td><td>bulb of by itself<sup>1,3–6,8–12</sup> or soaked in milk [pig]<sup>2,12</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Allium sativum</italic>
</td><td>bulb by itself [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>] or in milk [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Allium sativum</italic>
</td><td>bulb mixed with oil [dog] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], or in water [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>
<italic>Cucurbita pepo</italic>
</td><td>seed [pig]<sup>3,12</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Armoracia rusticana</italic>
</td><td>root with the pseudofruit of <italic>Juniperus communis</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Artemisia absinthum</italic>
</td><td>leaf as a decoction [dog] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>
<italic>Daucus carota</italic> ssp. <italic>sativus</italic>
</td><td>root [horse]<sup>7</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Avena sativa</italic>
</td><td>roated fruit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Artemisia herba-alba</italic> Asso (Asteraceae)</td><td>aerial part [sheep] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>
<italic>Quercus petraea, Q. robur</italic>
</td><td>nut [pig, cattle]<sup>3</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Cannabis sativa</italic>
</td><td>seed with lime-water, or with Allium cepa, goose fat and milk [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Chelidonium majus</italic> L. (Papaveraceae)</td><td>leaf in water [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>
<italic>Secale cereale</italic>
</td><td>fruit as fodder [horse]<sup>7</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Cucurbita pepo</italic>
</td><td>seed with the seed of <italic>Ricinus communis</italic> L., (Euphorbiaceae)</td><td>
<italic>Chenopodium ambrosioides</italic> L. (Amaranthaceae)</td><td>aerial part [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>whey powder</td><td>[pig]<sup>2</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Dryopteris filix-mas</italic> (L.) Schott, (Dryopteridaceae)</td><td>dried rhizome [poultry] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Daphne gnidium</italic>
</td><td>bark [swine, cattle, sheep, dog, horse] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic>
</td><td>roasted seed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Hypericum maculatum</italic> Crantz (Hypericaceae)</td><td>aerial part as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> L. Fabaceae</td><td>fruit as a decoction without salt [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Mentha suaveolens</italic> Ehrh.(Lamiaceae)</td><td>aerial part as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Quercus petraea, Q. robur</italic>
</td><td>ground nut or bark as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Ruta chalepensis</italic>
</td><td>aerial part [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Sambucus nigra</italic>
</td><td>bar kin milk [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Scabiosa columbaria</italic> L. (Caprifoliaceae)</td><td>aerial part as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Secale cereale</italic>
</td><td>fruit or flour [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Simethis mattiazzi</italic> (Vand.) Sacc. (Xanthorrhoeaceae)</td><td>root as a decoction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>
</td><td>bran with butter, fat, salt and soap as a decoction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Teucrium scorodonia</italic> L. (Lamiaceae)</td><td>aerial part [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>bran</td><td>with ash [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>dove dung</td><td>dried dung mixed into the fodder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>petroleum</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td>diarrhea</td><td>
<italic>Artemisia absinthium</italic>
</td><td>herb as a tea [cattle, horse]<sup>3</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Achillea collina</italic> (Becker ex Rchb. f.) Heimerl, <italic>A. millefolium</italic> (Asteraceae)</td><td>aerial part as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Achillea millefolium</italic>
</td><td>aerial part [calf] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>
<italic>Potentilla anserina</italic>
</td><td>leaf as a tea [cattle, horse, pig, sheep]<sup>1,2,4–6,9–12</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Alchemilla vulgaris</italic> L. (Rosaceae)</td><td>aerial part as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Achillea ptarmica</italic> L. ssp. <italic>pyrenaica</italic> (Sibth. ex Godr.)</td><td>flower with the flower of <italic>Sambucus nigra</italic> as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>
<italic>Rumex acetosella, R. obtusifolius</italic>, <italic>Rumex</italic> spp.</td><td>fruit as a tea [cattle, horse, pig, sheep]<sup>1–12</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Alnus glutinosa</italic> (L.) Gaertn. (Betulaceae)</td><td>bark as a decoction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Agrimonia eupatoria</italic> L. (Rosaceae)</td><td>aerial part as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>
<italic>Quercus petraea, Q. robur</italic>
</td><td>bark as tea [pig]<sup>3</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Artemisia absinthium</italic>
</td><td>aerial part as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Brassica oleracea</italic> ssp. <italic>oleracea</italic>
</td><td>aerial part [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>“hótszén”</td><td>as fodder [pig]<sup>2</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Aesculus hippocastanum</italic> L. (Sapindaceae)</td><td>seed [cattle, pig] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Ceratonia siliqua</italic> L. (Fabaceae)</td><td>grain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Chelidonium majus</italic>
</td><td>aerial part as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Chelidonium majus</italic>
</td><td>leaf as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Equisetum arvense</italic> L. (Equisetaceae)</td><td>aerial part as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Citrus limon</italic> (L.) Burm. (Rutaceae)</td><td>epicarp of the fruit with the seed of <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L. (Poaceae) as a soup [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Fagus sylvatica</italic> L. (Fagaceae)</td><td>bark as a decoction [cattle] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Eriobotrya japonica</italic> (Thunb.) Lindl. (Rosaceae)</td><td>leaf as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic>
</td><td>roasted seed [pig, horse] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], or with salty flour with the seed of <italic>Secale cereale</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Daphne gnidium</italic>
</td><td>stem [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Juniperus communis</italic>
</td><td>pseudofruit as a tea [cattle] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Foeniculum vulgare</italic> Miller (Apiaceae)</td><td>aerial part [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Quercus cerris</italic> L.</td><td>ground bark as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Hypericum maculatum</italic>
</td><td>aerial part as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Quercus petraea</italic>
</td><td>ground bark in fodder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Lythrum salicaria</italic> L. (Lythraceae)</td><td>aerial part [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Rumex acetosa</italic> L., <italic>R. confertus</italic> Willd., <italic>R. crispus</italic>
</td><td>seed as a decoction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Phlomis purpurea</italic> L. (Lamiaceae)</td><td>aerial part [sheep, horse, dog] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Rumex acetosella</italic>
</td><td>seed as a decoction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Quercus rubra</italic> L. (Fagaceae)</td><td>branch [rabbit] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Rumex patientia</italic> L., <italic>R. stenophyllus</italic> Ledeb.</td><td>[cattle, horse, pig] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Polygonum aviculare</italic> L. (Polygonaceae)</td><td>aerial part as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Ruta graveolens</italic> L. (Rutaceae)</td><td>aerial part as a tea [cattle] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Potentilla reptans</italic> L. (Rosaceae)</td><td>aerial part as a tea [rabbit] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Sambucus racemosa</italic> L. (Adoxaceae)</td><td>fruit as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> L.</td><td>aerial part as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Sisymbrium strictissimum</italic> L. (Brassicaceae)</td><td>root as a decoction [cattle] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Rumex acetosella</italic>
</td><td>aerial part [cattle] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> L. (Solanaceae)</td><td>tuber with the leaf of <italic>Robinia pseudoacacia</italic> L. (Fabacaeae) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Rumex</italic> sp.</td><td>boiled seeds in water [pig] [64]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Sorbus domestica</italic> L. (Rosaceae)</td><td>bark as a decoction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Thymus serpyllum</italic> L. ssp. <italic>nervosus</italic> (Willk.) Nyman (Lamiaceae)</td><td>aerial part as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>
</td><td>bran by itself [calf] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Vaccinium myrtillus</italic> L. (Ericaceae)</td><td>raw or dried fruit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>ash</td><td>[horse] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Verbascum sinuatum</italic> L. (Scrophulariaceae)</td><td>flower as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>salt</td><td>[sheep] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>vinegar</td><td>[sheep] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td>diuretics</td><td>
<italic>Petroselinum crispum</italic>
</td><td>leaf [horse]<sup>3</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Allium cepa</italic>
</td><td>bulb as a decoction [cattle, horse] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>], or into the urethra [horse] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Daphne laureola</italic> L.</td><td>aerial part [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>ammonia</td><td>to smell in the stable [horse]<sup>5,6</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Capsicum annuum</italic> convar. <italic>longum</italic>, (Solanaceae)</td><td>fruit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Herniaria hirsuta</italic> L. ssp. <italic>cinerea</italic> (DC.) Coutinho (Caryophyllaceae)</td><td>aerial part [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>lice</td><td>put into the urethra [horse]<sup>5</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Fragaria vesca</italic> L. (Rosaceae)</td><td>root as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Rorippa nasturtium-aquaticum</italic> (L.) Hayek, (Brassicaceae)</td><td>as a decoction [pig] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>water</td><td>poured beside the animals [horse]<sup>7</sup>, or put into the shed to vaporize and induce urination [sheep]<sup>7</sup>; animals guided to the edge of rivers to hear the sound of water [horse]<sup>5</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Narcissus stellaris</italic> Haw. (Amaryllidaceae)</td><td>flower [cattle] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Simethis mattiazzi</italic> (Vand.) Sacc. (Xanthorrhoeaceae)</td><td>root [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Petroselinum crispum</italic>
</td><td>leaf or root with saltpeter as a decoction [cattle, horse] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Zea mays</italic>
</td><td>stigma as a decoction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Peucedanum</italic> sp. (Apiaceae)</td><td>boiled herb as fodder [sheep] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Polygonum bistorta</italic> L. (Polygonacaeae)</td><td>rhizome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Sambucus nigra</italic>
</td><td>flower as a decoction [cattle] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Urtica dioica</italic> L. (Urticaceae)</td><td>root as a tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td>cataract</td><td>powdered sugar</td><td>blown into the eyes [cattle]<sup>1–12</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Anagallis arvensis</italic> L. ssp. <italic>phoenicea</italic> Vollmann (Primulaceae)</td><td>dried and ground petals mixed with powdered sugar [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>powdered glass</td><td>blown into the eyes [cattle]<sup>1–12</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Capsicum annuum</italic>
</td><td>dried and ground pungent fruit [cattle] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Malus sylvestris</italic>
</td><td>vinegar of the fruit as an embrocation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Matricaria chamomilla</italic>
</td><td>tea of the flower as a wash [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic>
</td><td>ground leaf spit with saliva into the eyes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Tilia cordata</italic> Mill. (Malvaceae)</td><td>yellow part under the bark with milk as an embrocation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>“szentgyörgybéka” (<italic>Bombina variegata</italic> L., Bombinatoridae)</td><td>put into the eyes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>ash</td><td>blown into the eyes [cattle] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>salt</td><td>blown into the eyes [horse] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>sugar</td><td>blown into the eyes [cattle] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>powdered glass</td><td>blown into the eyes [horse] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>powdered porcelain</td><td>blown into the eyes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td>after delivery</td><td>
<italic>Petroselinum crispum</italic>
</td><td>leaf to promote expulsion of the placenta as fodder [cattle]<sup>3</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> convar. <italic>vulgare</italic>
</td><td>roasted seed as fodder [cattle] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td>antiparasitic, repellent, and insecticide effect; for scab</td><td>
<italic>Juglans regia</italic>
</td><td>leaf against flies as a rub [horse]<sup>6</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Aconitum moldavicum</italic> Hacq. (Ranunculaceae)</td><td>root against lice and ticks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Capsicum annuum</italic>
</td><td>fruit in oil [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td>
<italic>Veratrum album</italic>
</td><td>ground root as a rub against lice, flies and mosquitos [horse]<sup>6</sup>
</td><td>
<italic>Artemisia absinthium</italic>
</td><td>aerial part strewed against lice, spray with lime in the chicken pen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Cestrum parqui</italic> L 'Hér. (Solanceae)</td><td>herb [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Ballota nigra</italic> L. (Lamiaceae)</td><td>aerial part put under hen against lice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Juglans regia</italic>
</td><td>leaf against flies as a decoction [horse] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Brassica oleracea, B. oleracea</italic> var. <italic>capitata</italic>
</td><td>sour sap of the leaf against scab [sheep] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], salty leaf sap against ox warble fly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>] and lice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Laurus nobilis</italic> L. (Lauraceae)</td><td>fruits in olive oil [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Cucurbita pepo</italic>
</td><td>runner against flies as a rub [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Matricaria chamomilla</italic>
</td><td>flowering top against fleas [cattle, sheep, dog] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Dryopteris filix-mas</italic>
</td><td>leaf as bed of straw [pig] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Olea europaea</italic> var. <italic>europaea</italic>
</td><td>seed oil as a repellent poultice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Euonymus europaeus</italic> L. (Celastraceae)</td><td>dried and ground fruit against lice [cattle, hen, pig] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Pteridium aquilinum</italic> (L.) Kuhn (Dennstaedtiaceae)</td><td>leaf against fleas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Helianthus annuus</italic>
</td><td>seed oil smeared onto the animals against lice [cattle, hen, pig] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Ruta chalepensis</italic>
</td><td>aerial part against flies as a rub [horse] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], and against fleas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Helleborus purpurascens</italic>
</td><td>root as a decoction against scab [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Sonchus oleraceus</italic>
</td><td>aerial part in oil and as a poultice against flies [horse, cattle] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], leaf and root as a decoction against lices, and as a bath against scabs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], root as a decoction and wash against lice and scabs [sheep] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Juglans regia</italic>
</td><td>leaf against flies as a rub [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Urginea maritima</italic> (L.) Baker (Asparagaceae)</td><td>bulb in oil [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], or placed in shed as a repellent [cattle] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic>
</td><td>leaf as a wash against lice, scabs and moths [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</td><td>
<italic>Veratrum album</italic>
</td><td>aerial part as a tea [sheep] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], root [calves] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Persica vulgaris</italic> Mill. (Rosaceae)</td><td>sap of the ground leaf smeared onto the body against flies [pig] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Polygonum lapathifolium</italic>
</td><td>leaf as a wash against lice, scabs and moths [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Rumex crispus</italic>
</td><td>root against scab as a decoction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Tussilago farfara</italic> L. (Asteraceae)</td><td>leaf against scab as a decoction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>
<italic>Veratrum album</italic>
</td><td>root dried and smeared onto the hair [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>], or boiled with the leaf sap of <italic>Brassica oleracea</italic> against lice [sheep, cattle], or with goose fat [hen] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>cart-grease</td><td>as a rub against lice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>copper sulphate</td><td>in water with vinegar as a wash [sheep] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>fat</td><td>rancid fat against lice [hen], or with mercury [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>lye-ashes</td><td>smeared onto the body [pig, sheep] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>petroleum</td><td>smeared onto the body [pig, sheep] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="top"><td/><td/><td/><td>potash-lye</td><td>in water as a bath [poultry] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</td><td/><td/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<italic>*Number superscipts refere to the specific villages studied in Covasna:</italic> Biborţeni<sup>1</sup>, <italic>Bodoş</italic>
<sup>2</sup>
<italic>,</italic> Filia<sup>3</sup>, Racoşul de Sus<sup>4</sup>, Băţanii Mici<sup>5</sup>, Băţanii Mari<sup>6</sup>, Herculian<sup>7</sup>, Tălişoara<sup>8</sup>, Aita Seacă<sup>9</sup>, Ozunca-Băi<sup>10</sup>, Vârghiş<sup>11</sup>, Valea Zălanului<sup>12</sup>. Full botanical citations for plants documented in this study are provided in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      <p>A total of 45 ingredients were documented in this survey, including 26 plant taxa (18 wild and 8 cultivated species; 57.8%), 2 animals (4.4%), and 17 animal-based substances, minerals or materials of other source (37.8%). Considering the frequency of citations, the use of <italic>Allium sativum, Aristolochia clematitis, Armoracia rusticana, Potentilla anserina, Rumex acetosella,</italic> and <italic>R. obtusifolius,</italic> as well as <italic>Mustela nivalis,</italic> “szénamurha”, powdered glass, sugar and water showed the highest prevalence (Tables <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p>
      <p>The highest number of remedies involving plants were for the treatment of diarrhea (7 taxa), as anthelmintics (6), for rumination (5), stomach problems and wounds (4), while a few taxa were cited for mastitis (3), respiratory ailments and as a repellent drug (2) (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Local names of plants varied from 1 to 6 per species. Some names correspond with the official Hungarian terminology using in single form or with vernacular names together (vernacular names are listed in italics in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p>
      <p>Regarding the plant parts used, the whole herb was the most frequently used part of the cited taxa (21.9%) followed by leaf and fruit (18.6% each), root (15.6%), bark (9.4%), flower (6.3%), pseudofruit, seed and bulb (3.2% each) (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Herbal remedies were applied internally and externally as a single tea (40%) or tea mixture (2.8%), in raw form as fodder (37.2%), in washes (8.6%), rubbing agents (5.7%), creams and liniments (2.8% each). Plants containing toxic compounds (e.g. <italic>Aristolochia clematitis</italic>, <italic>Veratrum album</italic>) are only reported for external use. In the case of <italic>Eryngium planum</italic> and <italic>Matricaria chamomilla,</italic> two types of preparation were mentioned, similarly to the application of salt, vinegar and water.</p>
      <p>Preparations based on other substances are commonly used with other materials (73.7%), with plants (5.3%), or in single form (21%) as a liniment, wash or fodder (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Although modern veterinary practice is expensive and not as easily available as homemade remedies, the use of injectable medicaments was also noted in the region (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p>
      <p>Comparing data recorded in the selected 12 villages, the use of <italic>Armoracia rusticana</italic> for respiratory illness in horses, <italic>Rumex</italic> spp. for diarrhea, and the application of sugar and glass powders for cataracts in cattle proved to be consistent and a commonly used treatment in each community surveyed (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Intracultural variance was documented in the frequency of some records, such as in the use of <italic>Allium sativum</italic> as an anthelmintic drug (in 10 villages), <italic>Aristolochia clematitis</italic> for wounds and <italic>Potentilla anserina</italic> against diarrhea (in 9 villages). There were also some interesting cases of unique ethnoveterinary practices that were restricted to one village each. For example, <italic>Gentiana asclepiadea</italic> (Figure <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>) was used with milk for stomach disorders; clay or water with salt for mastitis; <italic>Juniperus communis,</italic> “szénamurha” with urine and turpentine for respiratory ailments; cooking oil, <italic>Cucurbita pepo</italic> and <italic>Petroselinum crispum</italic> to improve rumination; the use of <italic>Eryngium planum</italic> and <italic>Euphorbia amygdaloides</italic> for wounds; <italic>Quercus</italic> species for diarrhea and as an anthelmintic drug used similarly to whey powder; “hótszén” against diarrhea; and <italic>Petroselinum crispum</italic> to dispel the placenta in cattle after delivery.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Root of <italic>Gentiana asclepiadea</italic> L.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13002_2015_20_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
      <p>Some similarities were found between the indications reported earlier in other Transylvanian regions and other countries, and the present uses of home remedies for mastitis, skin problems, diarrhea, cataract, and in anthelmintic and diuretic drugs (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).</p>
      <p>Compared to the earlier records in Transylvania, we found 18 similar uses of the following (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>, Figure <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>): <italic>Calendula officinalis</italic> flowers, as well as water with vinegar and salt to treat mastitis; <italic>Armoracia rusticana</italic> for respiratory ailments in Racu [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>] and Lueta [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]; <italic>Aristolochia clematitis</italic> for external injuries in Ţara Călatei [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>] and Homoród; and <italic>Euphorbia amygdaloides</italic> in Homoród [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] and Ghimeş [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. <italic>Allium sativum</italic> has been documented in Romania for its widespread use as a vermifuge [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>], similar to reports from Spain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], Algeria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], and Italy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Similar to our findings, <italic>Quercus</italic> spp. fruits have been reported as vermifuges in Homoród [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. The anti-diarrheal effect of <italic>Q. rubra</italic> has been observed in Morocco [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], and similar use of <italic>Q. ilex</italic> ssp. <italic>ilex</italic> have been reported in Catalonia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], corresponding to our data on <italic>Quercus petraea</italic> and <italic>Q. robur</italic>. Furthermore, the use of <italic>Artemisia absinthium</italic> has been reported for diarrhea in Homoród [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], while for <italic>Rumex</italic> species (which are well-known for their anti-diarrheal effects), the use of <italic>R. acetosella</italic> has also been described in Lueta [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>] and Croatia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. In contrast to the documented use of <italic>Petroselinum crispum</italic> leaves in the present work, the root has been recorded as a diuretic drug in Racu [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>], Ţara Călatei [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>], and Ghimeş [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>].<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Overlaps of ethnoveterinary data involving plant- and animal-based materials and other substances used in Covasna County, Pyrenees, Italian and Albanian Alps [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13002_2015_20_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p>
      <p>For respiratory disorders, the cones of <italic>Juniperus communis</italic> were mentioned as a fodder in our survey, but as a tea in Moldova [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], while in Algeria the leaf of <italic>J. phoenicea</italic> has been documented [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. The use of <italic>Salix alba</italic> has been similarly reported for rumination in Homoród [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>], while <italic>S. purpurea</italic> has been documented in Albania [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. In addition to the treatment of rumination disorders, <italic>Petroselinum crispum</italic> is used by itself in Covasna, but with bran in Trei Scaune [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. In contrast to the use of <italic>Polygonum minus</italic>, the leaf of <italic>P. lapathifolium</italic> has been observed for wounds in Ghimeş [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. The seed of <italic>Cucurbita pepo</italic> has been used for skin problems by itself in Covasna, but with castor oil in Harghita County [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>].</p>
      <p><italic>Veratrum album</italic> root has been reported as a widespread repellent and antiparasitic drug in Covasna [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], Ghimeş [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], Ţara Călatei [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>], Trei Scaune [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>], Moldova [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], and Lueta [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. <italic>Juglans regia</italic> leaves have also been reported for their use as a repellent in Harghita County [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Similar use of sugar and powdered glass has been observed for cataract in Ghimeş [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], Ţrei Scaune [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>], and Moldova [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>].</p>
      <p>Comparison is represented between our data and those of the mountain regions of Pyrenees, Italian and Albanian Alps, which covers the overlap of each ingredient (Figure <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Similar to our records, the use of <italic>Achillea millefolium</italic> was mentioned for rumination and digestive disorders in the Lombardy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>] and Albanian Alps [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. As anti-lice treatment, the root of <italic>Veratrum album</italic> was mentioned in Italy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>], and the aerial part of the plant in Catalonia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Similar to our records, <italic>Allium sativum</italic> was documented as vermifuge in Galicia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], <italic>Rumex</italic> species against diarrhea [64], and haemostatic use of cobweb and milk for intestinal aches in the Albanian Alps [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].</p>
      <p>Rituals and beliefs connected to local uses were sporadically mentioned in the region. The skin of <italic>Mustela nivalis</italic> was reported against udder inflammation caused by weasel bites, similarly to data recorded in Uz-valley [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. To stimulate urination, animals should hear the sound of rippling stream or poured water (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).</p>
      <p>Some of the present uses were not found in earlier Transylvanian reports nor in databases of other countries, such as remedies for “hotness” and for applications following delivery (e.g. for stimulating expulsion of the placenta). In addition, several practices are no longer used today, but rather survive only in the memory of the villagers, such as the use of cobweb for wounds, “hótszén” for diarrhea, and the placement of lice into the urethra as a diuretic.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec7" sec-type="conclusion">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>From an ethnoveterinary point of view, Covasna has proven to be one of the most interesting regions of Romania due to the diversity of knowledge concerning plant-, animal- and other substances-derived remedies. These traditions are practiced mostly by the more elderly subset of the population, forming a significant part of the local animal healthcare and cultural heritage of the region. Although some data survive only as memories from the past, people are proud of their traditional knowledge, which is still maintained in rural areas. In addition, holders of this knowledge have an important role as natural resource managers.</p>
      <p>Although ethnoveterinary service is cheaper and easily available compared to modern veterinary medicine and pharmaceuticals, factors such as the size and prevalence of herds, as well as the frequency of citation of traditional ethnoveterinary practices are diminished in comparison to earlier records of Romania, and other European countries. This change has also been influenced by shifting socio-cultural factors concerning local economies and emigration patterns, as well as less frequent opportunities for the vertical transmission of traditional knowledge. Future studies to support our further understanding of the role that ethnoveterinary practices can play in managing animal health are certainly merited. Such studies are useful not only for the purposes of folkloric preservation, but can also form a foundation on which to support sustainable development efforts aimed at promoting environmentally friendly, cost-effective means of maintaining livestock health.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Competing interests</bold>
        </p>
        <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Authors’ contributions</bold>
        </p>
        <p>SGB, LB and NP conducted the fieldwork. SGB and NP performed the comparative literature analysis. CLQ performed statistical analyses of the data. All authors participated in the writing and revision process and read, discussed and approved the final manuscript.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ack>
      <p>We are grateful for the help and contributions of the study participants. This work was supported by a grant from the OTKA (Hungarian Scientific Research Fund, PD 108534).</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McCorkle</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An introduction to ethnoveterinary research and development</article-title>
          <source>J Ethnobiol</source>
          <year>1986</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>129</fpage>
          <lpage>149</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Conti</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Letteratura popolare capracottese</source>
          <year>1911</year>
          <publisher-loc>Napoli</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>L. Pierro</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Blanco</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Macía</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morales</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Medicinal and veterinary plants of El Caurel (Galicia, northwest Spain)</article-title>
          <source>J Ethnopharmacol</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>65</volume>
          <fpage>113</fpage>
          <lpage>124</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0378-8741(98)00178-0</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10465651</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pieroni</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Quave</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nebel</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heinrich</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ethnopharmacy of the ethnic Albanians (Arbëreshë) of northern Basilicata</article-title>
          <source>Italy Fitoterapia</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>73</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>217</fpage>
          <lpage>241</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0367-326X(02)00063-1</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pieroni</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Giusti</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Münz</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lenzarini</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Turković</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Turković</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ethnobotanical knowledge of the Istro-Romanians of Zejane in Croatia</article-title>
          <source>Fitoterapia</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>74</volume>
          <fpage>710</fpage>
          <lpage>719</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fitote.2003.06.002</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14630181</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pieroni</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Howard</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Volpato</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Santoro</surname>
              <given-names>RF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Natural remedies and nutraceuticals used in ethnoveterinary practices in inland southern Italy</article-title>
          <source>Vet Res Commun</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>55</fpage>
          <lpage>80</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/B:VERC.0000009535.96676.eb</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14989363</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pieroni</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dibra</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grishaj</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grishaj</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maçai</surname>
              <given-names>SG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Traditional phytotherapy of the Albanians of Lepushe Northern Albanian Alps</article-title>
          <source>Fitoterapia</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>76</volume>
          <issue>3–4</issue>
          <fpage>379</fpage>
          <lpage>399</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fitote.2005.03.015</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15890470</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pieroni</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Giusti</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>de Pasquale</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lenzarini</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Censorii</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gonzáles-Tejero</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>RUBIA project: Circum-Mediterranean cultural heritage and medicinal plant uses in traditional animal healthcare: a field survey in eight selected areas within the RUBIA project</article-title>
          <source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>15</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-2-15</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16556305</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pieroni</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rexhepi</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nedelcheva</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hajdari</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mustafa</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kolosova</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>One century later: the folk botanical knowledge of the last remaining Albanians of the upper Reka Valley, Mount Korab, Western Macedonia</article-title>
          <source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>22</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-9-22</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23578063</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pieroni</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nedelcheva</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hajdari</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mustafa</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scaltriti</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cianfagliore</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Local knowledge on plants and domestic remedies in the mountain villages of Peshkopia (Eastern Albania)</article-title>
          <source>J Mt Sci</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>180</fpage>
          <lpage>193</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11629-013-2651-3</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pieroni</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Local plant resources in the ethnobotany of Theth, a village in the Northern Albanian Alps</article-title>
          <source>Genet Resour Crop Evol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <fpage>1197</fpage>
          <lpage>1214</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10722-008-9320-3</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Leporatti</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Impieri</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ethnobotanical notes about some uses of medicinal plants in Alto Tirreno Cosentino area (Calabria, Southern Italy)</article-title>
          <source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>34</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-3-34</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17983476</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Guarrera</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leporatti</surname>
              <given-names>LM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ethnobotanical remarks on Central and Southern Italy</article-title>
          <source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>23</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-3-23</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17537240</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Guarrera</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lucchese</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Medori</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ethnophytotherapeutical research in the high Molise region (Central-Southern Italy)</article-title>
          <source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>7</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-4-7</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18334029</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Montesano</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Negro</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sarli</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sarli</surname>
              <given-names>AD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Laghetti</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hammer</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Notes about the uses of plants by one of the last healers in the Basilicata Region (South Italy)</article-title>
          <source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>15</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-8-15</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22546322</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Carrió</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rigat</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garnatje</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mayans</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parada</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vallès</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Plant ethnoveterinary practices in two Pyrenean territories of Catalonia (Iberian Peninsula) and in two areas of the Balearic Islands and comparison with ethnobotanical uses in human medicine</article-title>
          <source>Evid Based Complement Alternat Med</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>2012</volume>
          <fpage>896295</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2012/896295</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22829861</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Di Sanzo</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Martino</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mancini</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Feo</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Medicinal and useful plants in the tradition of Rotonda, Pollino National Park, Southern Italy</article-title>
          <source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>19</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-9-19</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23522331</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Borza</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Dictionar etnobotanic</source>
          <year>1968</year>
          <publisher-loc>Bucharest</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Editura Academiei Republicii Socialiste Romania</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kóczián</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pintér</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Szabó</surname>
              <given-names>LG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Adatok a gyimesi csángók népi gyógyászatához</article-title>
          <source>Gyogyszereszet</source>
          <year>1975</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>226</fpage>
          <lpage>230</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kóczián</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pintér</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gál</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Szabó</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Szabó</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Etnobotanikai adatok Gyimesvölgyéből</article-title>
          <source>Bot Közlem</source>
          <year>1976</year>
          <volume>63</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>29</fpage>
          <lpage>35</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kóczián</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Szabó</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Szabó</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Etnobotanikai adatok Kalotaszegről</article-title>
          <source>Bot Közl</source>
          <year>1977</year>
          <volume>64</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>23</fpage>
          <lpage>30</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Péntek</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Szabó</surname>
              <given-names>TA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Egy háromszéki falu népi növényismerete</article-title>
          <source>Ethnographia</source>
          <year>1976</year>
          <volume>87</volume>
          <issue>1–2</issue>
          <fpage>203</fpage>
          <lpage>225</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Butura</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Encilopedie de etnobotanică românească</source>
          <year>1979</year>
          <publisher-loc>Bucharest</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Editura Ştiinţifică şi Enciclopedică</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Miklóssy</surname>
              <given-names>VV</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Csíki népi sebtapaszok</article-title>
          <source>Népismereti dolgozatok</source>
          <year>1980</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>60</fpage>
          <lpage>63</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Halászné</surname>
              <given-names>ZK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Adatok a moldvai magyarok gyógynövény-használatához</article-title>
          <source>Gyogyszereszet</source>
          <year>1981</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>361</fpage>
          <lpage>367</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rab</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Újabb népgyógyászati adatok Gyimesekből</article-title>
          <source>Gyogyszereszet</source>
          <year>1982</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>325</fpage>
          <lpage>333</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bosnyák</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Adalékok a moldvai csángók népi orvoslásához</article-title>
          <source>Orvostort Kozl</source>
          <year>1973</year>
          <volume>69–70</volume>
          <fpage>279</fpage>
          <lpage>298</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11627410</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gub</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Adatok a Nagy-Homoród és a Nagy-Küküllő közötti terület népi növényismeretéhez</article-title>
          <source>Néprajzi Látóhatár</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>1–2</volume>
          <fpage>95</fpage>
          <lpage>110</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gub</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Kertek, mezők termesztett növényei a Sóvidéken: Sóvidéki etnobotanika</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <publisher-loc>Odorheiu Secuiesc</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Erdélyi Gondolat</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gub</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Zsigmond</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Népi növényismeret a Nagy-Homoród mentén</article-title>
          <source>Növények a folklórban</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <publisher-loc>Bucharest</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>A Magyar Köztársaság Kulturális Intézete</publisher-name>
          <fpage>148</fpage>
          <lpage>62</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Grynaeus</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Szabó</surname>
              <given-names>LG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A bukovinai hadikfalvi székelyek növényei 1–4</article-title>
          <source>Gyogyszereszet</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <issue>Suppl 1–4</issue>
          <fpage>251</fpage>
          <lpage>259</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Halász</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>A moldvai magyarok hagyományos állattartása</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <publisher-loc>Budapest</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>General Press</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Halász</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Növények a moldvai magyarok hagyományában és mindennapjaiban</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <publisher-loc>Budapest</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>General Press</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kosz</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Czégényi</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keszeg</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Népi gyógyászat Csíkrákoson</article-title>
          <source>A beteg ember. Betegségek, betegek és gyógyítók</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <publisher-loc>Târgu Mureş</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Mentor Kiadó</publisher-name>
          <fpage>15</fpage>
          <lpage>108</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Benkő J: Transilvania sive Magnus Transilvaniae Principatus olim Dacia Mediterranea dictus… Pars prior sive generalis, Tom I, II. Vindobonae. Pars posterior speciali., Tom III. IV, V. (manuscript); 1778.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR36">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Baumgarten JCG: Enumeratio stirpium magno Transsilvaniae principatui. Tomus I, II, III. Vindebonae; 1816.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR37">
        <label>37.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schur</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Botanische Rundreise durch Siebenbürgen</source>
          <year>1859</year>
          <publisher-loc>Hermannstadt</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Verlandlungen und Mitteilungen des Siebenbürgischen Vereins für Naturwiss</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR38">
        <label>38.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Simonkai</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Erdély edényes flórájának helyesbített foglalata</source>
          <year>1887</year>
          <publisher-loc>Budapest</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Kir. Magyar Természettudományi Társulat</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR39">
        <label>39.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Römer</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Beiträge zur Flora von Kovászna</article-title>
          <source>Arch Verein Siebenbürg Landesk Neue Folge</source>
          <year>1895</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>561</fpage>
          <lpage>572</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR40">
        <label>40.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rácz</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kisgyörgy</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Füzi</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Kovászna megye Oltmenti gyógynövényei</article-title>
          <source>Orvosi Szemle</source>
          <year>1971</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>408</fpage>
          <lpage>412</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR41">
        <label>41.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rácz</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Füzi</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Kovászna megye gyógynövényei</source>
          <year>1973</year>
          <publisher-loc>Sfântu Gheorghe</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Directory of Agriculture, Food and Hydrography</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR42">
        <label>42.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Papp</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bartha</surname>
              <given-names>SG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Balogh</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Jelenkori etnobotanikai értékű adatok egy erdélyi (nagybaconi) falusi herbáriumból</article-title>
          <source>Bot Közlem</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>100</volume>
          <issue>1–2</issue>
          <fpage>177</fpage>
          <lpage>199</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR43">
        <label>43.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bartha</surname>
              <given-names>SG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Népi gyógynövényismeret Erdővidéken. MSc Thesis</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <publisher-loc>Pécs</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>University of Pécs</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR44">
        <label>44.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kisgyörgy</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Kovászna megye</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <publisher-loc>Miercurea Ciuc</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Pallas-Akadémia Könyvkiadó</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR45">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">The International Society of Ethnobiology Code of Ethics. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ethnobiology.net/code-of-ethics">http://ethnobiology.net/code-of-ethics</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR46">
        <label>46.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tutin</surname>
              <given-names>TG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burges</surname>
              <given-names>NA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chater</surname>
              <given-names>AO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Edmondson</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heywood</surname>
              <given-names>VH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moore</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Flora Europaea</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR47">
        <label>47.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Boris</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Népi gyógynövényismeret a székelyföldi Lövétén. BSc Thesis</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <publisher-loc>Pécs</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>University of Pécs</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR48">
        <label>48.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Péntek</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Szabó</surname>
              <given-names>TA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Ember és növényvilág. Kalotaszeg növényzete és népi növényismerete</source>
          <year>1985</year>
          <publisher-loc>Kriterion</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Bucharest</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR49">
        <label>49.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Papp</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Birkás-Frendl</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bencsik</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stranczinger</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Czégényi</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Survey of traditional beliefs in the Hungarian Csángó and Székely ethnomedicine in Transylvania, Romania</article-title>
          <source>Rev Bras Farmac</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>141</fpage>
          <lpage>152</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bjp.2014.03.005</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR50">
        <label>50.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Papp</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Birkás-Frendl</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farkas</surname>
              <given-names>Á</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pieroni</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An ethnobotanical study on home gardens in a Transylvanian Hungarian Csángó village (Romania)</article-title>
          <source>Genet Res Crop Evol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>60</volume>
          <fpage>1423</fpage>
          <lpage>1432</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10722-012-9930-7</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR51">
        <label>51.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Grasser</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schunko</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vogl</surname>
              <given-names>CR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Gathering “tea” – from necessity to connectedness with nature. Local knowledge about wild plant gathering in the Biosphere Reserve Grosses Walsertal (Austria)</article-title>
          <source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>31</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-8-31</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22889066</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR52">
        <label>52.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Passalacqua</surname>
              <given-names>NG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fine</surname>
              <given-names>DF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guarrera</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Contribution to the knowledge of the veterinary science and of the ethnobotany in Calabria region (Southern Italy)</article-title>
          <source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>52</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-2-52</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17156472</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR53">
        <label>53.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Akerreta</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Calvob</surname>
              <given-names>MI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Caveroa</surname>
              <given-names>RY</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ethnoveterinary knowledge in Navarra (Iberian Peninsula)</article-title>
          <source>J Ethnopharm</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>130</volume>
          <fpage>369</fpage>
          <lpage>378</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2010.05.023</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR54">
        <label>54.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vitalini</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Iriti</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Puricelli</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ciuchi</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Segale</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fico</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Traditional knowledge on medicinal and food plants used in Val San Giacomo (Sondrio, Italy). An alpine ethnobotanical study</article-title>
          <source>J Ethnopharm</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>145</volume>
          <fpage>517</fpage>
          <lpage>529</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2012.11.024</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR55">
        <label>55.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pieroni</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maria Giusti</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Alpine ethnobotany in Italy: traditional knowledge of gastronomic and medicinal plants among the Occitans of the upper Varaita valley, Piedmont</article-title>
          <source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>32</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-5-32</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19895681</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR56">
        <label>56.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pieroni</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cianfaglione</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nedelcheva</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hajdari</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mustafa</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Quave</surname>
              <given-names>CL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Resilience at the border: traditional botanical knowledge among Macedonians and Albanians living in Gollobordo, Eastern Albania</article-title>
          <source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>31</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-10-31</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24685013</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR57">
        <label>57.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jarić</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Popović</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mačukanović-Jocić</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Djurdjević</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mijatović</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karadžić</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An ethnobotanical study on the usage of wild medicinal herbs from Kopaonik Mountain (Central Serbia)</article-title>
          <source>J Ethnopharm</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>111</volume>
          <fpage>160</fpage>
          <lpage>175</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2006.11.007</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR58">
        <label>58.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Map of the study sites in Covasna County. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://earth.google.com">https://earth.google.com</ext-link>. 2015. Assessed 03 March 2015.”</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR59">
        <label>59.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pieroni</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Pardo-de Santayana</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pieroni</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Puri</surname>
              <given-names>RK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>People and Plants in Lëpushë. Traditional Medicine, Local Foods and Postcommunism in a Northern Albanian Village</article-title>
          <source>Ethnobotany in the New Europe. People, Health and Wild Plant Resources</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Berghahn</publisher-name>
          <fpage>16</fpage>
          <lpage>50</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR60">
        <label>60.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Akerreta</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rita Cavero</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Calvo</surname>
              <given-names>MI</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>First comprehensive contribution to medical ethnobotany of Western Pyrenees</article-title>
          <source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>26</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-3-26</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17553138</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR61">
        <label>61.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Agelet</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Valle’s</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Studies on pharmaceutical ethnobotany in the region of Pallars (Pyrenees, Catalonia, Iberian Peninsula). Part I. General results and new or very rare medicinal plants</article-title>
          <source>J Ethnopharm</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>77</volume>
          <fpage>57</fpage>
          <lpage>70</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0378-8741(01)00262-8</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR62">
        <label>62.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bonet</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Valle’s</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ethnobotany of Montseny biosphere reserve (Catalonia, Iberian Peninsula): Plants used in veterinary medicine</article-title>
          <source>J Ethnopharm</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>110</volume>
          <fpage>130</fpage>
          <lpage>147</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2006.09.016</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR63">
        <label>63.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Vofkori L. Utazások Székelyföldön. Miercurea Ciuc: Pro-Print Könyvkiadó; 2004.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

