<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JIMD Rep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JIMD Rep</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>JIMD Reports</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">2192-8304</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2192-8312</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Berlin, Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25701267</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4470955</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">384</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/8904_2014_384</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A Retrospective Survey Studying the Impact of Fabry Disease on Pregnancy</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Holmes</surname>
            <given-names>Alexandrea</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>Alexandrea-Holmes@ouhsc.edu</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff8"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Laney</surname>
            <given-names>Dawn</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff9"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff8"><label/>University of Oklahoma Health Sciences Center, 1200 Children’s Ave, Suite 12100, Oklahoma City, OK 73104 USA </aff>
        <aff id="Aff9"><label/>Department of Human Genetics, Emory University, Atlanta, GA USA </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group content-type="collaborators">
        <contrib contrib-type="Editor-in-chief">
          <name>
            <surname>Zschocke</surname>
            <given-names>Johannes</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1">Division of Human Genetics, Medical University Innsbruck, Innsbruck, Austria </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="com">
          <p>Communicated by: Verena Peters</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>22</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>21</volume>
      <fpage>57</fpage>
      <lpage>63</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>29</day>
          <month>09</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>08</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>13</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© SSIEM and Springer-Verlag Berlin Heidelberg 2014</copyright-statement>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <p>Fabry disease (FD) is a lysosomal storage disorder resulting from a deficiency of lysosomal enzyme α-galactosidase A (α-gal A). Reduced or missing α-gal A enzyme results in the storage of globotriaosylceramide (GL3) and related glycosphingolipids in the cellular lysosomes throughout the body. The majority of GL3 buildup occurs in the body’s vasculature resulting in narrowed blood vessels and an increased risk for strokes, transient ischemic attacks, and deep vein thrombosis. Theoretical concerns have been raised about increased pregnancy complications in women affected by FD as glycosphingolipid storage has been found in both maternal- and fetal-derived placental tissues. This retrospective study was conducted to better understand risks for women with FD during pregnancy. Survey questions included queries about prenatal medications, teratogenic exposures, prenatal testing, common pregnancy complications, Fabry symptoms during pregnancy, obstetrical history, and immediate neonatal history. In total, 41 affected women completed the survey. Results indicate several Fabry-related symptoms and features may worsen during pregnancy, including gastrointestinal symptoms, acroparesthesias, proteinuria, headaches, and postpartum depression. Although no life-threatening complications were reported, a statistically significant increased frequency of hypertension was observed when comparing data from this study to the general population (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) and previous publications (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001). Limitations include sample size and recall bias. Though this survey sampling of women was small and required women to recall their past pregnancy experiences, the findings suggest that when pregnant, women with FD should be aware of potential worsening of FD symptoms and may benefit from consulting with a maternal-fetal medicine specialist.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>© SSIEM and Springer-Verlag Berlin Heidelberg 2015</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
</article>

