<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="abstract">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Online J Public Health Inform</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Online J Public Health Inform</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">OJPHI</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Online Journal of Public Health Informatics</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1947-2579</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>University of Illinois at Chicago Library</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4512373</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ojphi-07-e121</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5210/ojphi.v7i1.5787</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>ISDS 2014 Conference Abstracts</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Comparison of ILINet and ESSENCE for Influenza Surveillance at the
Local Level</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Connolly</surname>
            <given-names>Sarah</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup> 3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Danyluk</surname>
            <given-names>Gregory</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup> 2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Florida Department of Health, Seminole County,
Sanford, FL, <country>USA</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Epidemiology, Florida Department of Health, Polk
County, Bartow, FL, <country>USA</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Emory University, Laney Graduate School, Atlanta, GA,
<country>USA</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Gregory Danyluk, E-mail: <email xlink:href="gregory.danyluk@flhealth.gov">gregory.danyluk@flhealth.gov</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>26</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>7</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <elocation-id>e121</elocation-id>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>ISDS Annual Conference Proceedings 2014. This is an Open Access
article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons
Attribution-Noncommercial 3.0 Unported License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>), permitting all
non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the
original work is properly cited.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>© 2015 the author(s)</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords: </title>
        <kwd>ESSENCE</kwd>
        <kwd>ILINet</kwd>
        <kwd>Influenza surveillance</kwd>
        <kwd>Influenza-like illness surveillance</kwd>
        <kwd>Influenza</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Objective</title>
      <p>To compare influenza-like illness (ILI) data reported to the Centers for Disease
Control and Prevention (CDC) U.S. Outpatient Influenza-like Illness Surveillance
Network (ILINet) with discharge diagnosis data for influenza from the same reporting
source obtained through the Electronic Surveillance System for the Early
Notification of Community-based Epidemics (ESSENCE) in Seminole County, Florida.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>ILINet is used nationwide by sentinel healthcare providers for reporting weekly
outpatient visit numbers for influenza-like illness to CDC. The Florida Department
of Health receives urgent care center (UCC) data through ESSENCE from participating
facilities. Seminole County is unique in that its four sentinel providers located in
separate UCCs report into both systems, and all their discharge diagnoses are
available through ESSENCE. However, the reported number of patients being discharged
from those providers with diagnoses of influenza is not equivalent to the number of
cases reported into ILINet. Data from the two systems were therefore compared both
among and between the individual sentinel providers in order to determine the extent
of the variation over four influenza seasons.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <p>Influenza-like illness is defined by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention
(CDC) for surveillance purposes as “fever (temperature of 100°F
[37.8°C] or greater) and a cough and/or a sore throat without a KNOWN cause
other than influenza.” [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] ILINet data
from sentinel providers for percent ILI visits were extracted for each of the
influenza seasons (reporting weeks 40 through 20 of the following year) from 2009
through 2013. ESSENCE data for patients with a discharge diagnosis of influenza were
extracted from the same providers for the same seasons, and the percentage of
influenza discharge diagnoses was calculcated based on total visit counts. Pearson
correlation coefficients were calculated to compare ILINet and ESSENCE data for each
influenza season and provider location, both for the entirety of the season as well
as identified peak weeks (Table 1); for the few instances where ILINet data had not
been reported, those weeks were not included in the calculations.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>When data from all four providers were aggregated for each respective surveillance
system, the correlation between ILINet and ESSENCE discharge diagnoses of influenza
ranged from 0.53 to 0.89 over the entirety of each season, and from 0.45 to 0.86 for
peak weeks (Table 2). By contrast, the correlation by individual provider between
the two systems ranged from 0.02 to 0.77 over each season, and from -0.15 to 0.92
for peak weeks (Table 3).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>Although the correlations between the surveillance systems ILINet and ESSENCE were
positive when viewed in aggregate, individual sites demonstrated inconsistency in
reporting. This study demonstrates a need to identify the sources of differences
that occur between making and reporting a determination of ILI versus those involved
in a discharge diagnosis of influenza</p>
      <fig id="fa" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Table 1</label>
        <graphic xlink:href="ojphi-07-e121-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="fb" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Table 2</label>
        <graphic xlink:href="ojphi-07-e121-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="fc" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Table 3</label>
        <graphic xlink:href="ojphi-07-e121-g003"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>We wish to thank the epidemiology staff of the Florida Department of Health in
Seminole County, their counterparts at the Florida Department of Health in Orange
County, and the staff at the Bureau of Epidemiology for the Florida Department of
Health in Tallahassee, in particular David Atrubin for ESSENCE assistance, and Colin
Malone for his comments regarding statewide influenza surveillance. We also extend a
deep appreciation to the ILINet sentinel healthcare providers for their continued
participation.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="r1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="web">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention
(US). Overview of Influenza Surveillance in the United States [Internet].
Atlanta. [updated 2013 October 24; cited 2014 August 29]. Available from:
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/flu/weekly/overview.htm">http://www.cdc.gov/flu/weekly/overview.htm</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

