<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Clin Exp Pathol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Clin Exp Pathol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ijcep</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>International Journal of Clinical and Experimental Pathology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1936-2625</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>e-Century Publishing Corporation</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26261488</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4525822</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Knockdown of microRNA-127 reverses adriamycin resistance via cell cycle arrest and apoptosis sensitization in adriamycin-resistant human glioma cells</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Feng</surname>
            <given-names>Ren</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dong</surname>
            <given-names>Lei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="au1">
          <label>1</label>
          <institution>Department of Medical Administration, Tianjin Huanhu Hospital</institution>
          <addr-line>Tianjin 300060, China</addr-line>
        </aff>
        <aff id="au2">
          <label>2</label>
          <institution>Department of Pediatrics, Division of Hematology/Oncology, Aflac Cancer and Blood Disorders Center, Emory University School of Medicine</institution>
          <addr-line>Atlanta, GA 30322, USA</addr-line>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp><bold>Address correspondence to:</bold> Dr. Ren Feng, Department of Medical Administration, Tianjin Huanhu Hospital, Tianjin 300060, China; E-mail: <email>fengren_tjh@126.com</email>; Dr. Lei Dong, Department of Pediatrics, Division of Hematology/Oncology, Aflac Cancer and Blood Disorders Center, Emory University School of Medicine, Atlanta, GA 30322, USA. E-mail: <email>ldong8@emory.edu</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>01</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>6107</fpage>
      <lpage>6116</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>07</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>IJCEP Copyright © 2015</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The aim of this study was to investigate signaling pathways for reversal of microRNA-127-mediated multi-drug resistance (MDR) in gliomas cells. Adriamycin-resistant glioma cell lines U251/adr and U87-MG/adr were established and we found that anti-microRNA-127 markedly reduced microRNA-127 expression levels in a time-dependent manner, leading to distinct inhibition of cell proliferation and increased apoptosis and the content of intracellular Rh123. Silencing of microRNA-127 significantly increased the sensitivity of U251/ADR and U87-MG/adr cells to adriamycin, compared to cells transfected with negative control siRNA. Silencing of microRNA-127 also significantly reduced the mRNA and protein expression levels of MDR1 and MRP1, which are major ATP-binding cassette (ABC) transporter linked to multi-drug resistance in cancer cells. And Runx2, p53, bcl-2 and survivin, which are important role in cell apoptosis, also markedly changed after microRNA-127 silencing. In addition, down-regulating microRNA-127 decreased the level of phosphorylated-Akt. Our data indicate that down-regulation of micorRNA-127 can trigger apoptosis and overcome drug resistance of gliomas cells. Therefore, this resistance of adriamycin in gliomas can be cancelled by silencing expression of microRNA-127.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>microRNA-127</kwd>
        <kwd>gliomas</kwd>
        <kwd>adriamycin</kwd>
        <kwd>drug resistance reversal</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
</article>

